Councilman C. Grave, can you uh just say
hello to everyone?
>> Hello everyone.
This little technical trouble here.
Dr. Emmens, can you hear us?
>> I can. Can you hear me?
>> Yes. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen.
Thanks for your patience as we work
through some technical difficulties in
the booth. But uh at this time, I'd like
to call the September 14th meeting of
the governing body to order and ask our
clerk if she would take the role.
>> Mr. Wolf
>> here.
>> Dr. Aldrich present. Mayor Collins
>> Dr. Emmens
>> here.
>> Mr. Esel
>> Mr. Lebornne
>> here.
>> Mr. Moody
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Mr. Crave
>> present.
>> Mr. White
>> One member is absent. We do have a
quorum.
>> Would you please join me in the pledge
of allegiance?
>> I pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Number four, consent agenda. All agenda
items listed with the designation of CA
are considered to be routine items by
the governing body and will be enacted
by one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body. So
requests and support by two other
members is received. Any item moved from
the consent agenda will be considered in
its normal sequence on the agenda.
>> All right. Just uh a little point of
information for people watching on Zoom
tonight. Apparently our video is not
working. Uh people can hear us. if they
want to watch us, they have to go to
YouTube. And I guess our YouTube feed is
working tonight. Our our camera there
is, but for some reason, our video for
Zoom is not working. Uh, but people can
participate online. They just won't be
able to see our lovely faces in the
process. And with that, I'll ask if
there's anything uh a member of the
governing body would like to remove from
the consent agenda. And I see Mr.
Labour, you have your light on.
[clears throat]
>> Number 18.
>> Concur.
>> Okay. Number 18 has been removed from
the consent agenda
>> and
>> number 26
>> B
>> D is in David
>> E.
>> Okay.
>> Concur.
>> Any others?
Hearing none, I would entertain a
motion.
>> So move
>> second.
>> Been moved by Mr. Crave and seconded by
Mr. White. All those in favor of the
consent agenda with items 18 and 26D
removed, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed, the consent agenda is
approved as amended with numbers 18 and
26D removed. They'll be taken in their
normal sequence on the agenda.
>> Mr. Mayor, Mr. Crave.
>> I move to suspend the rules to change
the order of the agenda to allow for the
consideration of item 29A, appointment
of Andrew Sickenberger to municipal
court judge prior to item number 6A.
>> We have a motion and a second to change
the order of the day to move item number
29A to um be the next item on our
agenda. Um, all those in favor of that
motion, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. All right, we'll move
that item up. And madame clerk, if you
would read that into the record, please.
>> Number 29A, appointment of Andrew
Sickenberger to municipal court judge.
>> Hang on a second. U Mr. Mayor, um, under
Robert's rules of order, chapter 6,
subsidiary motions, there is an option
for limiting or extending limits of
debate in
>> Can we take that after we do this item,
please?
>> Sure.
>> I'd appreciate that. Thank you very
much.
Go ahead and read that for me, please.
>> 29A, appointment of Andrew Sickenberger
to municipal court judge.
>> All right. We uh had an opening for a
municipal judge. Um we did interviews
and uh one of our magistrates, Andrew
Sikenberger, was the uh person selected
by the committee to uh to make that
selection. Uh I would entertain a motion
to uh approve Mr. Sickenberger as our
newest municipal judge.
>> So move
>> second moved by Dr. Aljids, seconded by
Mr. Crave. Uh comments on the
appointment question.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank Mr. Mayor through you. Just a
couple questions. Um when was the
gentleman admitted to the bar? What
year?
>> Um Mr. Sikenberger, could you come
forward and answer that question because
quite frankly I don't remember.
>> Certainly. Mr. Mayor,
>> can you push that button and turn the
microphone on? Thank you.
>> Certainly, Mr. Mayor. Through you, Mr.
Mayor, to Councilman Moody. I was
admitted to the bar in September of
2021.
>> Okay. Follow, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you, and
uh what is your prior experience?
>> Mr. Mayor, through you a clarifying
question uh to Councilman Moody, just
generally with the law, sir.
>> Uh experience in the courtroom, defense
attorney, prosecutor. That's what I'm
looking for.
>> Mr. Sikenberger.
>> Mr. Mayor, I threw you to Councilman
Moody. I started at Woodhouse Road in
Ames as Brennan uh during my first year
and a half or so of practice. I've
practiced uh in numerous trial courts uh
family court uh general civil litigation
largely dealing with negligence and
insurance defense. Uh that was at my
third job. Uh after I left Woodhouse
Roaden, I was the public defender for
the city of Cheyenne for about a year.
Uh and then I left that I was at
Buckhammer and Ward uh PC for two years
doing general practice uh criminal
family that civil litigation contracts
arbitration.
So I have
pretty much since I graduated and before
that when I was uh working at a clinic
at the University of Wyoming College of
Law. Uh since that time I've been doing
criminal practice and in courtrooms.
>> And Mr. Mr. Kimberger, you are currently
one of our magistrates working in the
court.
>> That is correct, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yeah. Thank you. Thank you. Any other
questions? All right. Hearing none. All
those in favor of the appointment,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Okay. Mr. Moody is a no. The appointment
is approved. And Madame Clerk, would you
please swear the justice in?
>> Raise your right hand. Repeat after me.
I state your name.
>> I, Andrew Sikenberger,
>> do solemnly swear. do solemnly swear
>> that I will support the Constitution and
laws of the United States
>> the Constitution and laws of the state
of Wyoming
>> and the charter and ordinances of the
city of Cheyenne
>> and that I will faithfully, honestly,
and impartially
>> And that I will faithfully, honestly,
>> discharge the duties of municipal court
judge
>> of the city of Cheyenne. of the city of
Cheyenne.
>> To the best of my ability and
understanding.
>> to the best of my ability and
>> Congratulations.
>> Thank you. Congratulations,
[applause]
>> Andrew. Congratulations. And your honor,
welcome to the the court.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Dr. Aldish, I understand you wanted the
floor.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mayor Collins. Um, under
Robert's rules of order, chapter 6,
subsidiary motions, there is an option
for limiting or extending limits of
debate in section 15. It appears that
the council may establish limits on
debate by a two-thirds vote, which can
include limiting the amount of time each
member may speak. A motion to limit
debate is not debatable. Um, for
example, the council could adopt a
motion that each member be allowed one
speech of three minutes on a pending
motion. And once that motion's been
approved, the chair can enforce that
limitation during the discussion. Um,
therefore, I move that the debate on all
items this evening be limited to one
speech of three minutes per member on
each item.
>> Second.
>> All right, we have a motion and a second
to limit speech for, as I take it, Dr.
Aldridge, not only members of the
audience, but also members of the
governing body.
>> That's correct.
>> Okay. Um, it's a non-debatable motion.
All those in favor of limiting our time
speaking this evening, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands or the nose, please?
Mr. Moody, Mr. Wolf, and Mr. Leborn, the
motion is approved. Tonight, we will
have a a time limit of three minutes per
speaker. Uh, and it looks like we'll be
limited to one speech per item. Uh, with
that, we'll go into our next item,
please. Um, Madame Clerk,
>> clarification, sir, that's for the
members of the governing body.
>> Yes, sir. That's correct.
>> Next item is 6A. Public hearing to
determine whether compliance of
annexation conditions required by
Wyoming statute 15-1-402
exists for about 162.42 acres of land
located west of South Gley Highway south
of West College Drive and southwest of
and adjacent to the intersection of
Apple Street and York Avenue.
All right, we'll open a public hearing
then to take uh comment on this um
annexation. And the first thing we're
going to do is have a brief staff
report. Mr. White,
>> mayor, members of council, Connor Way,
Planning and Development Department.
There we go. The or this annexation is
for roughly 162.42 42 acres of land
generally located west of South Gley
Highway, south of West College Drive and
southwest of the inner southwest and
adjacent to uh the intersection of Apple
Street and York Avenue.
The city received petition to annex this
land from the owners which was filed
with the city clerk on July 13, 2026.
This petition was certified by the city
clerk as containing the necessary
signatures according to state statute on
July 17th, 2026. This public hearing is
being held in accordance with Wyoming
state statute 15142A.
Pursuant to fulfilling the requirements
in state statute, staff asks asks the
governing body to consider the
following. The land proposed to be
annexed is contiguous to current city
limits. Specifically, the property is
25.26%
contiguous.
uh all city services and utilities are
available to the properties
um or available to the property within
the city um will be provided to the
annex land. Extending water and sewer
increases the health, safety of
individuals uh living and working in
this area of the community. Water and
sewer uh is actually adjacent to the
property on both the west, south, and
east side.
The area to be annexed is inside the
urban service boundary and designated
with mixeduse residential on the future
land use map. This type of development
is best supported by being within city
limits and connecting to city services.
Certified mailing was sent to all land
owners and utilities within the annexed
area not less than 20 business days
prior to the public hearing tonight.
According to the calendar, 20 uh 20
business days was August 14th and the
mailing was sent out on August 13th and
the earliest confirmed receipt was
August 17th. Uh property owners within
300 ft of the subject property were also
mailed notice uh within that time period
and the sanctation is being uh is
accompanied by an assigned zoning, a
future land use map amendment and a
zoning map amendment.
Before I get asked the question, um,
yes, we have had public comment on this.
Um,
we received a couple phone calls. Uh,
most of those phone calls, I would say,
were more interested in not really the
annexation. Uh, was more about the use
of the land, the future land use
amendment, that nature. Uh, we have had
a couple comments about the annexation.
Uh, those mostly being from those in, I
believe it's Orchard Valley. uh just
being concerned that this annexation
would basically make it easier for the
city to force annex them. Um that's not
the case. This doesn't create a county
pocket. It doesn't make them any more
contiguous to city limits. Um so that's
that's not really a concern that they
should have um because it wouldn't it
wouldn't make it easier um or change
anything in that regard. Other than
that, there wasn't there haven't been
any other uh public comments regarded to
the annexation itself
and I am available for any questions.
>> And Mr. White, this is a owner initiated
annexation, meaning the owner of the
property asked to be annexed.
>> Uh, mayor through you. Yes, that is
correct.
>> Okay. Any questions for staff from uh
members of the governing body? Mr.
Dwight, thank you. We'll go out to the
audience. Now, this is an opportunity if
you want to talk to us about the
annexation of what I believe is being
called the Orchard Hills area. And uh in
order to do that, if you could come up
to either one of the two microphones, uh
please give us your name and then we'll
take three minutes of your comments,
please. And Heather, do you want to
start us off or
you know how to do this? I figured you
might be a good role model.
>> Heather Madrid, Ward One. I guess my
only um concern is that I agree like
just annexing this one piece of property
isn't putting the rest of Orchard Valley
at risk of being annexed, but that's
typically not how this has been working.
It's they what it seems like people are
kind of creeping piecing together
annexations until
it justifies the annexation of a massive
chunk of land. Although I don't know
necessarily that's that that will happen
with Orchard Valley. From what I
understand, nobody wants to annex them
ever. But that's my concern with
annexations in general is that it's
never just one. It's a hopscotch game.
Seems like that's all.
>> Anyone else want to speak tonight on the
>> Good evening, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Um, Janet Tolman, Ward 2. Um,
I just would like to ask a question. It
just seems like
this piece of property that's being
requested to be annexed is next to
property that isn't annexed. Is that
correct?
>> I say that's true, ma'am. It's next to
an area that is already annexed. So,
it's contiguous to the existing city,
but it's also um next to some land
that's not been annexed. Yeah. So, it's
kind of in between. It's I think they
said 20 uh 25.26%
contiguous to the city. So, that means
about 75% of it doesn't touch the city.
>> Okay. And are the homes are those
already in the city or there some of the
homes not in the city? The area that's
being annexed, I don't has think has any
homes on it. It's it's it's
>> the I mean I mean the properties that
are next to it
>> um the the property to the south is
where the meta data center is, I
believe, and that is in the city limits
and the property to the north is um is
in the unincorporated county and those
are homes. You can see on the map now
they pulled it away so you can see it
better. There's a TV right there in
front of you if you make it easier or
behind you might be easier.
>> Mayor,
>> I could see the concern that they would
have because they're not in the city,
but then this property south of them is
wanting to be annexed into the city. And
so I
it would almost be like an encroachment.
I I'm not aware of the the laws but or
the rules of how um things are annexed
into the city, but it just seems like
yeah, it's more like not well planned
and it would it would be a good idea to
designate certain areas that could be
annexed and different areas that would
not be annexed into the city so that
there's a major plan
instead of just
one property asking to be annexed into
the city when there's uninccorporated
next to it. To me, it just doesn't make
any sense. Maybe it makes sense to other
people, but it doesn't make any sense to
me.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Mr. White,
>> mayor, uh Conway Planning Development
Department, I was just going to make a
clarifying uh comment for everybody. the
shaded red that's to the south of the
subject property, that is what is
currently annexed in the city. Um, so
basically anything in the shaded red is
city limits. Anything that's just not
shaded would be considered county.
[snorts]
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. White. Through you, Mr. Chairman,
Michael White. Um, I'd like to make a
point of order. Uh if you're going to
limit everybody on the council, you need
to you'll need to limit Connor White's
um time frame, too.
Point of order. So, if you guys are
going to start having rules that we have
to abide by out here in the public, then
you need to make sure that the staff has
the same rules.
>> Mr. White, do you have a comment on the
annexation?
>> Uh the annexation is um
I believe what the first speaker, the
second speaker thought. I I go back to
plan Cheyenne and also I go back to uh I
don't hear the report from the board of
public utilities because that's under
the southside certain water
jurisdiction. I think that these council
meetings with due respect for annexation
we need to understand the full um the
full comments by everything that goes to
the city planning department to to be
read into the record. I believe also
that we need to um update the rules for
annexation. Um annexation is a part of
this city and county that we seem to be
talking about every council meeting and
to your respect to you, Mr. Collins. I
realize that we can only talk about
annexation, but I believe that there has
been enough information. And I believe
there's enough people in the room that
are going to share their concerns, but I
think the sanation vote should be voted
down tonight. Thank you.
>> Sir, please.
>> Good evening, mayor and members of the
city council. My name is Jeff Nakushima
with Tremble Crow Company. I am here
tonight to speak in support of the owner
initiated annexation of the 162 acre
Orchard Hills property. While there's
understandably a lot of interest in
future zoning, tonight's decision is
strictly about annexation. It is about
whether it makes sense for this parcel
to be officially to officially join the
city of Cheyenne. Under Wyoming State
Statute 15-1-42,
this property satisfies and exceeds all
five of the state's legal criteria.
First, contiguity. The property is
immediately adjacent to the existing
city limits, making this a logical,
orderly expansion of the city's boundary
rather than a leaprog development.
Second, natural and integrated
development. This land is already
surrounded by high impact
infrastructure. There are already three
existing or planned electrical
substations on the property along with a
multitude of high voltage transmission
lines. Furthermore, we are immediately
adjacent to the 900 acre metadata center
campus. From an infrastructure
perspective, this land is already deeply
integrated. Third, service extension.
This property is uniquely plug-and-play.
All required municipal utilities are
already sitting at the property line.
The infrastructure is ready and we will
fund 100% of the costs to tie into those
existing lines, ensuring no financial
burden to Cheyenne taxpayers. Fourth,
health, safety, and welfare. This is
where the community wins. Unlike unlike
other developments, data centers
generate virtually no traffic.
Furthermore, by annexing this property,
we will help solve a major local
transportation issue by facilitating the
expansion of the Wallik and Parsley
roads. This will directly relieve
congestion at the new 56 grade school
and improve traffic safety for thousands
of surrounding residents. And to address
neighbors concerns that we've listened
to over the past couple of months, we
are proposing a substantial 500 plus
foot buffer to shield adjacent
properties that make better view sheds.
And we are fully prepared to put our
commitments to strict noise and zero
spill lighting mitigations in writing as
a binding condition of this project.
Finally, utility integration. We are
prepared to work with the city to
establish necessary franchise utilities.
Annexation is not an approval of a
specific building layout. It is a vote
for smart managed growth. It gives the
city of Cheyenne the steering wheel. By
voting yes on this annexation, you
ensure that Cheyenne city planners,
utility experts, and this city council
have the ultimate authority over how
this land is managed. We respectfully
ask for your support of this annexation.
Thank you very much.
>> Thank you, sir. Erin, did you want to
speak?
>> Yes.
>> Welcome
Madson. I am not sure which word I'm in.
I believe um
>> it doesn't matter. I know you live in
the city,
>> but Yeah.
>> Yeah. Welcome.
>> Well, here's my thing. I'm a biologist.
I was asked if I had done any research
on data centers whatsoever. Well, you
know what? Now I have. and the results
that I have seen so far are not good. I
don't understand why the um what makes
the council so sure that we are going to
be exempt from all the negative impacts
they've had in Tennessee and
Mississippi. Also, I know that they
said, "Oh, well, we'll just go way way
down to that water and use that water."
Well,
that is what the people who do fracking
do.
And so I start wondering whether if the
water is going to mix together. It is a
possibility
and there is an even greater possibility
that we will need that water on down the
line.
Now, I have to say that since none of
you presumably are scientists, I have
thought of several things that could go
wrong. There's data centers in water,
data centers in energy, data centers in
the environment, data centers and
pollution,
>> point
I apologize, Aaron, what we're talking
about right now is the annexation. I
think what you want to talk about is the
zone change which is coming up a little
bit later um you know in the meeting. So
>> do you have any comments on the
annexation itself bringing this land
into the city limit?
>> Sure. We all know what the annexation
for and these people they don't care
about us in this city.
>> Mayor point of clarification.
>> Yeah.
>> This is a correct me if I'm wrong. This
is a public hearing.
>> Yep.
>> And so no votes going to be taken on
this tonight.
>> That's correct. It'll be it'll be
referred to the public services
committee next week and come back in two
weeks for the first actual official vote
of this governing body. Thank you, sir.
Sir, please.
My name is Ross Ginsel and I live on the
border of uh this property and I'm kind
of in the uh world of realism. We know
it's going to get annexed. We're
surrounded by some development. Um,
I'm not happy about it. I'd love it to
stay wild, but that's not going to
happen. So, um, if it is annexed,
um, I think as Jeff had said that the
data center would be the softest blow to
everybody around us as far as, um,
traffic patterns, uh, high density u
development, high density development. I
think the data center is much better
right now. Um, we're receiving all the
lights from the current metadata center
all night long. It's never nighttime in
my house anymore. And uh,
so we know that it's going to be
annexed. We know that's going to that's
going to happen. But we're all, at least
the people I talked to who live on that
boundary are rooting for the data
center. So that would I know that's
coming up, but I want to get my opinion
on that. Sir, if you if you were to look
on that map, are you directly north then
of of the the area that we're we're
talking about?
>> Right off of Draper.
>> See where the power station is?
>> Yes, sir.
>> If you go over two streets,
actually one right on the corner there.
So, it's almost center of the boundary
line.
>> Okay.
>> So,
thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, ma'am. Welcome. Now, you
got to bring that microphone down and
talk right into it for us. There you go.
>> They're saying I'm short.
>> I didn't say that, but thank you.
[laughter]
>> This is Jay Leser. I am W and also in
the county. I would like to propose that
in the in the agenda that we put all the
things for the same property right next
to each other and we follow right
through. in the consent agenda, this
property is already um marked as
mixed use. But if you go to and that's
in the consent agenda 24. If you go to
15 and 16 in the agenda for some of the
people who are new to the things here um
realizing that later on it's going to be
changing the zoning and that should be
brought to light all at one time that
it's going to change the zoning from
agricultural to light industrial. So for
all the properties that we're talking
about tonight and in the future, let's
put all this topic about one property
together. Ma'am, we can't do that
legally.
>> You can't do that legally.
>> The state law says we have to have a
public hearing. That's what we're doing
now. Okay. And then after the public
hearing, then we get to put these things
on the agenda. So, the agenda is not to
be discussed today. They're just going
to be referred to committee. So, the
clerk will read them in and I'm going to
immediately assign them to a committee.
So, they won't be discussed at all
tonight. And then they will be in order
and next to each other next council
meeting. The annexation will be first,
the the assigned zoning will be second,
and then the zone change will be third.
They'll be actually in order that way.
But the law says we have to have a
public hearing before we can put them on
the agenda and that's what we're doing
here today.
>> Well, can you reference then from like
six in number six that to reference 15
and 16 at least something like that. So
that makes
>> others are aware.
>> Yes, ma'am. And you've made them aware
tonight. Thank you for that.
>> Appreciate you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
Please identify yourself and pull that
microphone down.
>> Thank you, mayor. My name is Susan
Gensel and I just live on the uh county
side of the annexed proposal property.
Uh in fact, my fence line is buted up
right against it and I'm not really in
favor of any changes right there. I like
the natural habitat there. So, I'm not
in favor of that. But I know a lot of
people want it annexed. But my concern
is I want to keep some sort of buffer. I
don't care if you want to do residents
or if you want to do
um data centers. I want a big buffer
between us and them. Uh what Jeff
suggested was that 560. So I don't care.
Like I said, if you want to do
residential
further south, I just I don't want the
road in front of us becoming a highway.
It's a dirt road. We have horses in the
area. We have goats. People raise beef
cattle and hogs
and livestock.
>> Understood. Thank you.
Anybody else want to speak on the
Orchard Hills,
what we call Orchard Hills in this
public hearing?
Anybody else in the audience? Anybody
online? Tina?
Okay, one more time and then I'm going
to close the public hearing.
All right, the public hearing is closed.
Go ahead. We just had a hand come up
just as before you said you were going
to close
>> in under the wire.
>> Yeah.
>> Mr. Smith, you may go ahead and speak.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> Go ahead.
>> Mayor Collins, members of the council,
Charles Miller. Um, this is in regards
to item number 6A. the public hearing on
the 162 acre annexation west of South
Gley Highway.
This hearing has one purpose, to
determine whether the conditions
required by Wyoming statute 15142 exist.
I wanted to point out that the that item
number six has no supporting document
attached on tonight's agenda. Um, the
only analysis the public could read is
buried in the item number 14, staff
report. If staff is relying on a
separate annexation report tonight, it
should be entered into the public into
the record before any finding is made.
Based on what is public, three
conditions are not met. First, health,
safety, and welfare of persons residing
in the area. Nobody resides there. Uh,
staff said the land is vacant. The
argument is that a future developer gets
city water. That's not a finding about
people living there and it says nothing
about the families um on Apple and York
who will have light industrial next
door.
Second, a logical and feasible addition
where services can be furnished within
reason. No cost estimate, no sewer
capacity number, no water demand figure
for a parcel the applicant told staff
verbally is a data center within reason
means somebody did the math. Nobody has
shown it. Third contiguity
uh staff's own number
uh 25.26
uh percent a quarter of the perimeter
touches the city. That's a flag pole,
not an extension.
and notice
uh
let's see here
the
report says the 20 business day deadline
was August 14th and the earliest con uh
confirmed delivery of the certified
mailing was August 17th after the
deadline.
Um
let's see here. Uh
the it looks like 6 days ago the
planning commission voted six to nothing
against the land use change on this
exact parcel and your own sta and your
own staff recommended denial. This
annexation exists for one reason to
enable a reszone. Your planners and your
commission both rejected.
um
if you could uh populate this report
with um the water, sewer, and fire
feasibility analysis uh before you make
any findings.
Um
>> Mr. Miller, thank you for your comments.
>> We have one more person that would like
to speak.
>> Please let him on.
>> Go ahead, Mr. Russell or Miss Russell.
Russell.
>> All right. Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you just fine, ma'am.
>> Awesome. My name is Paige Russell. I
live on the county side of the um
currently proposed annexation. I just
wanted to point out that there have been
five owner requested annexations that
have led to business park zoning. Um
especially in front of this council. In
order to address those annexations, then
we would have to address zoning. I know
that the council really wants us to talk
just about how this is annexation first
and then we'll talk about zoning. But
every annexation that we've had for the
past like few years has led to a
business park zoning. And so then we're
trying to talk about how we don't have a
problem with owner requested annexation.
In a lot of these cases, what we have is
the actual zoning that creates a
business park. And I think that those
impacts have to be talked about. Um and
so I just wanted to come here and make
sure that that was heard as well that
we've seen this um continued like uh
pattern happening and we're aware and
we're frustrated by um the council's
decision to continue uh running this
same ploy.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> All right. Is anybody else online?
Nope. Okay. We're going to close the
public hearing. Uh are there any
comments from members of the governing
body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. White,
>> just uh some point of information that
the developer and um folks associated
with the proposed project have held
three public meetings and they will be
holding another one this Thursday at 7
o'clock at Rossman Elementary.
>> Thank you, Mr. White. Plus, they have
really good barbecue. If you haven't had
Fred's barbecue, it's worth going just
to have a little piece of their brisket.
>> We should have received an invitation on
that this afternoon.
>> I think we did.
Yep.
>> Is open to the public.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Next,
>> sorry. It is this Thursday night, 700
p.m. at Rossman Elementary in the
gymnasium.
>> So, if you came to the meeting before,
you should get you should be getting an
email from what I saw. And um so
opportunity to come and learn more about
the project if you'd like to. And like I
said, they have great barbecue, so it's
worth it. All right. The purpose of the
public hearing has been
>> Yes. Like I was wondering if someone
could answer the question about the
lighting now during construction. So
we're talking about the meta property
and when we
heard from Microsoft that they had the
black shields over the lights after the
construction.
So is there someone that can tell us
what the difference is right now? Um
Mr. Bloom. Thank you.
Mayor, members of council, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. Um, during construction
activities, they um are not required to
fully comply with the lighting ordinance
because they are required to comply with
safety practices of in the industry
ocean standards and stuff. Um however we
do have uh communications with the
project managers if there are complaints
on lighting where u most of the
developers if not all of them have been
very responsive to moving lights and
changing them if there is a glare that
goes directly into somebody's homes. Um
but during the construction activities
there aren't uh the same requirements as
a permanent development where they are
required to be shielded. They're
required to stay on the property so the
lights aren't trespassing on on
neighbors lands.
Thank you, Mr. Bloom.
All right, the purpose of public hearing
has been met. We'll go on to the next
public hearing, please. Number 6B,
public hearing to determine whether
compliance of annexation conditions
required by Wyoming statute 15-1-42
exists for about 652.67
acres of land located south of
Interstate 80, southeast of Auto Road,
and west of Interstate 25.
Are you ready?
>> Yeah.
>> Please go ahead.
>> Okay. Mr. Mayor, members of the council,
Morgan Dennis, Planning and Development.
This annexation is for two parcels
totaling roughly 652.67
acres of land generally located south of
Interstate 80, southeast of Auto Road
and west of Interstate 25. The city
received a petition to annex this land
from the owners which was filed with the
city clerk on July 16th, 2026. This
petition was certified by the city clerk
as containing the necessary signatures
according to state statute on July 17,
2026.
This public hearing is being held in
accordance to Wyoming state statute
15-1-42A.
Pursuant to fulfilling the requirements
in the state statute, staff asked the
governing body to consider the
following. The land proposed to be
annexed is contiguous to the current
city limits, specifically the larger
property is 64.71%
and the smaller property is 80.68%.
All city services and utilities
currently available to residents of the
city will be provided to the properties
of the annex land. Extending water and
sewer sewer will increase the health and
safety of those in the air this area of
the community.
The area to be annexed is inside the
urban service boundary and is designated
as agricultural rural open space and
parks and mixeduse employment by the
future land use map. This type of
development is best supported by being
within city limits and connecting to
city services. Certified mailing was
sent to all land owners and utilities
within the annexed area no less than 20
business days prior to the public
hearing. According to the city's
calendar, 20 business days prior to
today's hearing was August 14th. The
certified mailing was sent out on August
13th and the earliest confirmation of
receipt was August 17th.
Property owners within 300 ft of the
subject property were also mailed public
notice within the same time frame. This
annexation is accompanied by an assigned
zoning, future land use map amendment,
zone change, and a delayed submitt of a
expedited plat. And to answer the public
uh public comment question that I know
Dr. Aldridge will have, um, [laughter]
we did not receive any public comment
regarding the annexation for this
project.
Miss Dennis, this is basically the
Hitching Post um annexation, correct?
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor. Yes.
>> And so for the audience, this is where
the Pro Rodeo Cowboy Association
headquarters where their Hall of Fame
and their museum will go. And it is
designed to be a uh uh an entertainment
uh area. Um, and as I understand, the
owner of this property has put a
requirement on there that it cannot ever
be a data center. Is that fair? Or maybe
you don't know that, but I know the the
developers do. it. That would be a
question for the developer, Mr. Mayor.
>> Okay, we can ask that question. So,
that's what the purpose of this
annexation is to uh provide water and
sewer for the new home for the PRCA. And
with that, we'll open this up to the
public,
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yeah,
>> I have some questions for
>> Go right ahead, sir.
>> Thank you. So, uh could we go back to
the map without the
timing?
So there in the lower uh right hand
corner is the proposed PRCA
uh area there um near to the McDonald's
and the truck stops. And so the upper
part that uh
you're circling the arrow in is not
immediately adjacent. So,
I'm I'm curious about how you're how
we're doing both at the same time. Is
that what we're doing?
>> Miss Dennis.
>> Um, Mr. Mayor, to Councilman Lebourne,
um, clarifying question. Are you asking
if we are annexing both parcels at the
same time?
>> Yes.
>> Yes, we are annexing both parcels at the
same time as they have the same property
owner. So, we can we can do that.
>> Well, it's a lot of property. Um, and
this is a question uh that I'm sure will
be coming up as we proceed with this.
I'm certainly uh very supportive
personally of the uh Hitching Post
project and the PRCA Hall of Fame. When
I look at that map and could we could we
go back to the colored map? I look at
that uh intersection of I80 and 20 I25
and I know that over time there's been a
lot of discussion about the
reconstruction of that entire
intersection
and I'm wondering if we can get some
information on when and how that might
occur because obviously it's going to
have some serious effects uh on that
area and um I'm really curious it seems
it. I know it was an incredible amount
of money. I know that we're uh probably
waiting for uh some future time, but can
someone answer for me what the status of
that uh reconstruction of those
interstates
is at this time?
>> Mr. Cobb, is that you or Mr. White? Do
you have the answer to that?
>> Well, I full disclosure, I work at White
Dot, but this is way out of my
wheelhouse. However, uh what I do know
is that number one, that project cost
would be in the billions and there is no
timeline. While I'm everyone would love
to have it done sooner than later, it is
on no timeline at all. Currently,
>> they're working currently on how how to
get a design done. Is that correct?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh to continue, Mr. Mayor, I think
there's a lot of interest and concern on
how that area there uh off I25
that is going to be the access to the
Hitching Post District and that bridge
with the crossover
arrangement.
Um, do we have any idea when that
situation might be improved so that uh
we didn't have uh a real
there's a lot of truck stops.
>> Mr. Emmens, do you have an answer to
when the double diamond or the
converging whatever you call that the
the diamond intersection? I
>> Mr. Mayor through you to the council. Um
the uh diverging diamond when it was
originally built the bridge was set up
to add two more lanes. Um so that will
be at some point need to be expanded and
widened. Um we have turned in a traffic
study for the High Plains District that
the city has and WTO has. So they're
currently reviewing the traffic study um
and they will be the deciding on when um
that expansion is going to have. I do
know I believe there was just an overlay
was currently on the step to do an
overlay in a year or two but I think
they're re-evaluating it now that this
project's going forward to make sure
that they're not overlaying it and then
tearing it all up um right away again.
So it's in white dot's hands to review
the traffic report and the timing of
those improvements. I would like to
point out what Mr. White was Councilman
White was talking about is the I25 I80
interchange. That's a lot further out
than the College Drive expansion. Um um
if I can speak to the couple of the
other questions that I do have the
answers for. Uh the reason the South
Blue area is being annexed is the road
um comes off of there and the actually
the PRCA and the Hall of Fame is in the
south I would call it the southwest
corner of Yeah. down in there. So, we're
annexing that other area so that we can
um plat the road to get from um college
down to the um APRCA and museum. And so,
that's why there's parcels the area
between the two blue is already in the
city. Um so, there was no ret no reason
to include that in the annexation.
>> Thank you, Mr. Emmens.
>> Thank you.
>> Anyone else? Okay, up to the audience.
We have the hitching post district for
the PRCA. Does anybody want to speak to
the annexation of this area?
Heather Ward one, sorry, talk about
everything, but I just have a question.
I'm not opposed to this annexation, but
I just wonder why we have all these
owner initiated annexations, but we
don't hear from the owners. We're
hearing from developers and planners. I
know one of the property owners I'm
pretty sure is here somewhere for the
previous
um discussion with the Orchard Hills
project and I just wonder if they're
owner initiated annexations why it seems
like they should be speaking for
themselves and especially if we're going
to be held to not talking about data
centers at an annexation but the person
speaking on behalf of the owner is a
data center developer. It just doesn't I
don't get it.
>> Heather I think Mr. Emmens was hired by
the owner to uh be his expert and to be
here on their behalf to speak and so
that's why they're here to do that.
>> Yeah, I I understand that. I just don't
what I don't understand is why there is
no expectation of any of the owners to
speak about these properties that they
want air next especially if they're
here.
>> It just doesn't make a lot of sense to
me.
>> Anybody else? Mr. Evans, you want to
answer that?
>> Mr. for mayor through you. Um,
currently, uh, Doug Samson, owner of
Swan Ranch, is out of town. He cannot
make tonight's public hearing, but he
is, um, scheduled to be in at the public
service meeting, so he can answer any
specific questions at that meeting as
well.
>> Thank you, Mr. Neper. Did you come speak
to us tonight?
>> I am coming.
>> Welcome back.
>> Um,
Mr. Mayor, members of the council, my
name is John Neper. I'm an attorney here
in Cheyenne, although I'm not here on
behalf of any uh client. So, I'm just
here in my personal capacity as a
resident of war. But I I did want to
sort of highlight a couple of things in
particular about this parcel. one, I I I
just want to remind the the council
something that can get lost in time,
which is just how um supportive of this
city in particular, this parcel, which
has been sort of looming out there is
something we've all known needed to
develop with, you know, years and years
of of questions about what could
actually be built there. Uh and and I
I'll just say that the current owner
when we were working with them 15 years
ago on uh issues of annexation and
consent to annexation, you know, they
they put even at that time significant
amounts of their own money in to make
sewer available. uh you know they
interestingly the water rights I think I
don't know if they're officially yet
belong to the city of Cheyenne but there
was a a strong there was an agreement
made 15 years ago that this that these
very old water rights are going to be
something that you know they can use
them for a now but ultimately they're
going to be something that BOPU is going
to be able to use to ensure that the
citizens of Cheyenne have priority in
any kind of drought you know to make
sure that you know the young women and
children of our city or young children
and women of our, you know, the families
of our city, the ones who are most
vulnerable in a time of drought are the
ones getting water. and and I'm just I'm
very supportive, not because of any
agenda, not because of any money, but I
just having worked with the property
owner 15 years ago, they were incredibly
um uh supportive of of the city and it's
thriving and and we're not asking I mean
there was not kind of any kind of
highway pulled up or any kind of deal
that was anything that's that was other
than than in the best interest of
everyone. The only other thing I would I
would just say generally about these
annexations and this is my experience
litigating some of these about 15 years
ago. Uh I understand a lot of the
concerns that folks have about you know
uh code construction etc. I'll just say
you know the the city staff here are
fantastic. I mean if you want fire
protection the city of Cheyenne Fire
Department is the place you wanted to
come from. If you want um if you want
people to monitor and help ensure that
you have water, you know, BOPU is doing
75 years out planning for water
availability for the city of Cheyenne. I
just I just I don't think there's anyone
better than our staff in terms of making
sure that that concerns are addressed
fairly and well. and and so if you know
when you have these concerns, I think
it's always better to have them
addressed and and and dealt with through
the city processes after annexation than
to try to, you know, hold it off and and
try to see whether or not the county,
which has got great people. I I think on
some areas they just don't have the
level of expertise that our city staff
have.
>> Thank you, Mr. Nipper. Appreciate it.
That's all I have. Anybody else on the
Hitching Post District before us this
evening?
How about online?
>> Yes. Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
Mr. Miller, did you put your hand back
down?
>> Okay. Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none, then the
purpose of the Well, let's see if
there's anybody on the We'll We'll close
the public comment and go to the city
council. Anybody on the governing body
want to speak to this?
>> Just a quick comment, Mr. Mayor. Mr. Um,
as someone who's supported this uh,
Hitching Post PRCA project from its
inception,
just a little bit of background that
that the county has submitted um,
investment money into this, the city
has, the state legislature did, and
recently the voters just did. So,
everybody, literally everybody's got
skin in the game on this important
project.
>> Mr. Esabel. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
through you and whatever we do with
access, I can tell you it's going to be
a heck of a lot better than what
Colorado Springs has for access to
theirs now. So, count on that. Amen.
All right. The purpose of the public
hearing has been met. And again, this
item will be uh the uh annexation and
the zone change will all be handled at
the next Monday's uh public service
committee meeting and then back here in
two weeks.
Next item, please. Number seven on page
two, ordinance second reading, annexing
to the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming, land
west of Round Top Road and adjacent to
HappyJack Road, postponed from April
27th, 2026.
>> All right. This is, I think, is most
commonly known as the Cox Ranch uh
annexation. It's an owner requested
annexation of 1,252.09
09 acres. And to my knowledge, um the uh
the folks who are asking for this
annexation have a data center planned
for this area. And so with that, we'll
open it up to the public to take any
comments you might have on item number
seven, which is the Cox Ranch
annexation.
>> Mr. White, welcome again. Uh through
you, Mr. Mayor Michael White. Um, at
public service committee, I voice my
opinion on um two properties that aren't
owned by the same people, which um the
skybox property and then the adjacent
property, which is the Board of Public
Utilities property. I believe we're
setting a bad precedent. And I will say
that again. I think I do respect BOPU
trying to do what they believed was a a
good intent, but I think these two
items, these two properties needed to be
separated. And I still believe that
tonight. Whether I'm the only one in the
room that believes that. Um I think that
we sent a bad president when we say we
can get two different project land
owners and put them in one. That's my
opinion only. And I believe that um as I
said before,
we know what's going to be there on the
other one. We're not allowed to talk
about it, but I believe we need more
ample time to address this. And I ask
that this be defeated tonight. Thank
you,
>> Mr. White. Respectfully, I'm going to to
disagree with you, and I just want to
like to people always ask us to act as a
business, right? To run the city like a
business and to try to uh save the
taxpayers money when we can. And when
they were annexing the Cox Ranch, they
had to go out with their surveyors and
do a survey of the ranch in order to do
the annexation. While their surveyors
were out there, we were able to get them
at a much less expensive rate because
they're already out there working. Um,
and it just made sense for us to do
that. There was no attempt to try to
slide in annexing city property. We can
annex it anytime we want. It just saved
us money. And if we're gonna act like a
business, that's what I think most
people ask us to do. Uh, we took
advantage of that. And there was no
attempt on anybody's part to do anything
that was um you know was trying to slide
a hand or give you more. It doesn't it
doesn't add to contiguity. It doesn't do
anything other than it just saved the
board of public utilities people uh the
rateayers money.
>> Well, if that was the case, Mr. Mayor,
through you then it should have been
brought up to council a long time ago
when the BOPU wanted to annex it. So, um
that's my opinion. I respect your
opinion. I'm not saying I said a public
service and the people that were public
service. I made points to say I I were
very respectful of Mr. Strong and his
staff and I did not in any way say that
they weren't professional. I just said
it should have been done where it was
two different properties, two different
owners and it should have been
separated. Thank you. You made your
point. Thank you, sir.
>> Mr. Mayor, council, thank you for the
opportunity to be here. Tom Galissmeer,
Vio Group. I'm here uh supporting the
annexation of the Cox Ranch property. Um
I want to speak to that one in
particular. Um it is owner petitioned
and meets the criteria. We are are
supporting it as a co-developer of a
project uh contemplated there. Uh we
want to be in Cheyenne. We want to be in
Wyoming. Uh we feel like our culture and
values overlap really well. um the
thoughtful design, um the
the way that Wyoming goes about growing
and
managing through growth, um is I think
very admirable and doing it doing doing
it thoughtfully um is is uh uh something
that we really appreciate. Um, I think
that this council uh made a wise
recommendation in April to postpone. It
allowed us uh to come up with a great
solution with the Cox uh and and black
families. Uh it was a privilege to work
with Miss Woodhouse getting that uh
solution uh finalized. Uh during this
postponement as well, we've hosted four
community openhouse meetings. We are
hosting our our fifth tomorrow at 12:30
at the library. Invite anyone to join.
Um it's Q&A open. Um we'll stay and
answer as many questions as people want,
whether it's about data centers or about
the proposed layout.
Um it's also been a great privilege to
get to know our direct neighbors, Mr.
Eley and Mr. Galotus. We've got uh uh
open lines of communication with them.
We really value their input and their
collaboration um in making uh what we
hope is a great project uh both from a
land use and water conservation
standpoint. Uh there'll be plenty of
open space for grazing and we uh really
feel like there's a lot of opportunity
to do a smart project um particularly as
it relates to our most precious resource
water. Um I'd [snorts]
also um like to share that we uh this is
just the just the beginning for us. Uh
we've we've joined a number of the um
local and and statewide organizations
including WHAM and the WBA. Um we were
participants in the county livestock
sale here and we have donated to meals
on wheels. We continue to we'll continue
to do that and that's is just the just
the beginning for us. We're uh we're
committed to the long run. Uh we uh as I
said earlier really uh want to be here
for uh the cultural and the uh the the
overlap in values of our companies and
uh the a lot of the people that we've
gotten to meet here. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Sir,
>> welcome. How are you tonight?
>> I'm good, Mr. Mayor. Thank you, Mr.
Mayor. Council members, Rick Kesler,
Rolling Hills Estates. Um, I'm here to
talk against the the annexation, not
against data centers, but the
annexation. Um, I think we should be
honest with each other tonight. Nothing
said here is going to change the way you
intend to vote on the Cox annexation,
but we can still tell you what we think.
So, we keep hearing that you're only
doing what the landowner wants. That
might be true if the landowner weren't
deceased. So, let's stop pretending this
is about honoring his wishes and this is
about advancing the financial interests
of lawyers in Florida and right here in
Cheyenne who stand to make millions if
you push this through. We've already
shown that this annexation does not
comply with Wyoming state statutes.
We've shown that your own planning
department ignored its own procedures.
Yet, you proceed as if none of that
matters. as if the law, the process, the
people affected are simply obstacles to
be brushed aside.
While researching this proposal, I
wondered how the North Range Business
Park was annexed. And the answer became
obvious the moment I looked at the maps.
It was done the only way it could be
done with smoke and mirrors.
Every person in this room should look at
those maps. It's a real eye opener.
What your planning department lacks in
procedure, it makes up for in
creativity. Even David Copperfield
doesn't have an illusion this impro
impressive in his repertoire. And
because the magic worked once or trying
it again, maybe no one will notice, but
this time we noticed.
The residents most affected by this
annexation have no voice in city
government. We cannot vote for mayor. We
cannot vote for city council members.
And yet you can oppose decisions that
will reshape
our neighborhood, our property, and our
daily lives. You hold all the authority,
and we bear all the consequences.
And I hate to say this, but there is one
thing we can influence, and that's your
pocketbook. You got a taste of that last
month when your municipal building
restoration request was defeated. It's
too late to affect the current round of
six penny requests, but I would suggest
that every Laram County resident and we
are all Lar Laram County residents
withhold support for any future optional
six penny requests tied to the city of
Cheyenne until you and our county
commissioners represent everyone, not
just a select few. Will withdrawing
support hurt small towns? Absolutely.
And that's precisely the point. It shows
just how far the consequences of this
annexation will reach. Not just for
those of us living next to it, but for
every community in Laramie County. Are
we against growth? Not at all. But we
are against decisions made without any
regard for how they will impact
surrounding neighborhoods. Decisions
made without transparency, without
accountability, and without the voices
of the people who live with results.
Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> [applause]
>> Guys, I know you're happy with what he
had to say, but you know, please refrain
from from cheering and and clapping.
Thank you, sir.
>> Uh, mayor and council men and women of
the council, thank you for the time. My
name is Jack O'Neal. I'm uh part of the
development group, part of this
annexation and I just want to say all
criteria have been met um for the
annexation by state statute and local
rules. And also I just wanted to throw
out one other thing on top of Tom's note
is that if anyone has any questions and
cannot make it to our fifth uh community
engagement meeting tomorrow, please feel
free to shoot an email to wyoming
skyboxdatacenters.com
and that will go directly to me. We also
have a phone number. You can call that
as well. It's a 307 number and I'll
respond to that uh within 24 hours. So,
please feel free to reach out. Don't be
a stranger. Uh we're here to be open,
honest, transparent, and continue the
conversation here um in regards to the
annexation. So, thank you for the time.
>> Anybody else want to speak,
>> Miss Madrid?
Heather Madre, Ward One. While I do
appreciate the lots and lots of
meetings, that isn't the same thing as
consent. Just because people come here
and participate in these meetings and go
there and participate in those, that
doesn't mean that we are okay with
what's happening. Um, you may have
noticed there are a number of people
here in green. There's about probably at
least 30 people here who don't want
this. They might not get up and say it,
but you can see them. Um,
there are probably some people here who
outright hate data centers, everything
they stand for, and don't want a single
one of them to begin with.
That ship left the harbor years ago. We
are now operating about 30 data centers
at 10 different locations. That number
is ever growing and there are no signs
of slowing down. In fact, it's picking
up rapidly. Most of us are here because
we reject irresponsible development of
any kind. We reject unregulated and
unchecked growth, arbitrary annexations
and resonings, and mostly we reject
being treated, as the gentleman before
me just said, as an obstacle for
developers to overcome with the help of
this council. and mayor, we are not
anti-progress. And if it feels like it's
a bias against one industry, that is
because you've acted as a concier
service for this particular industry
above all others.
We evidently want to protect our roads
and citizens from the trucking industry,
as we should. However, when it comes to
big tech, the idea of doing the same is
viewed as extortion. We don't want
Amazon trucks with three trailers
driving on our roads. But if Amazon
wanted to build five data centers here,
they would get the red carpet treatment.
This particular annexation went before
the public service committee last week
where it was stated by a council member
that if the data center development does
not move forward, it will become a
housing development and will rem will
remain in the county. This is also the
argument from the Traml Crow from Traml
Crow and that current property owner.
This is problematic for a few reasons.
One is it's a scare tactic for adjacent
property owners. Two is this is creating
a false dichotomy or a false choice. And
it's basically an admission that our
zoning laws and future land use map mean
absolutely nothing and a property can be
developed on completely opposite ends of
the spectrum. Either high density
housing or a data center and somehow
we're supposed to believe that our maps
and our laws mean anything.
um when it actually means that
properties can be developed on the whim
of the property owner. Three is that if
this is if this owner initiated
annexation meets statutory requirements
to be annexed, the law states that it
shall be annexed, not that it may be
annexed, which is a point that Mr.
Craves has made previously. So why will
it remain in the county if it becomes
homes but not if it's a data center? Is
it because this city wants as much tax
revenue as possible without having the
fiscal responsibility of taking care of
the humans who live here? If that's not
the very definition of putting corporate
interests above the interests of
citizens, I truly do not know what is.
Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am. Please welcome.
>> You got to push that button for me. Turn
on that microphone, please. There you
go.
>> Susan Roa. I live out um off a roundtop
where you're talking about the
annexation.
Um you know, I hear about the open
commun open and honest communication,
but then I read things like
what's going out there is not one data
center, but three data centers. That's
not open communication with the public.
If that is true,
um, you know, the citizen says, we're
expressing our concerns and quite
truthfully, I like others have commented
and stuff. I don't feel like we're being
listened to. I feel like a second rate
citizen. Okay. Um, and you've already
stated it yourself. You can enex
anytime. And I think that's been the
problem with the country anymore. you
know, we're not being listened to as
citizens. Um, you're you're taking I'm
reading here and I'm sure this is data
stored at the data centers. Okay? You
know, I'm reading here how the growth in
the electrical use that by 2030 that
these data centers, the increase in use
in electricity,
it's going to be half by these data
centers. Where does that leave the
everyday citizen? Okay, there's going to
be an increase in prices. Is the city
going to make up for their use? Because
they're a business, so they get the
cuts. Your everyday citizen does not get
a cut. We pay our dues. We pay our
bills. We live the best we can. And
like I said, you know, I am concerned
what's going to happen out there. I
understand growth and I understand the
need of it. But right now the US, we
have nine times more data centers
according to the data from the data
centers. Nine times more data centers in
the US than any other country.
And Cheyenne is growing like crazy with
data centers. So when is it enough? When
is it enough money? When is it enough?
because it's I it's just getting out of
hand at this point. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, ma'am.
Please.
>> Hi.
>> Hi. You're gonna have to bring it up.
>> Can you hear me? Okay.
>> I hear you. Great.
>> Okay. My name is Shelley Russell. I'm a
local contractor here in Cheyenne.
Um my concern is with the Cox Ranch
annexation.
I'm against it as you can see on my
shirt, but
do do you have in that area the
resources that you need for like fire
departments and so forth? Because I know
where I live out on Bison Crossing on
Terry Ranch Road, we've got all those
data centers going in and back in
February, we had a wildfire that
happened.
We were told to evacuate the area.
It usually takes me to get from my
house, which is right off of Terry Ranch
Road, to get down to the street to
um that gas station down there,
Mavericks. Usually takes me five minutes
on a normal day. It took me over an hour
when they evacuated us to get to there.
I had people that lived down the street
from me that were trying to get their
horse horses out of the area because the
fire was right there by my house. So
that's my concern for the people that
live out there because of with you know
they because not only we were evacuated,
Meta was evacuated, Microsoft was
evacuated, all of it. That was a heck of
a traffic jam. So that's my concern for
these people that live out there. I
think that needs to be taken into
consideration
also. Okay.
Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Good evening.
>> Good evening,
>> Mr. Mayor. Council Gay Woodhouse. I'm an
attorney. I work with Woodhouse, Rhden,
Ames, and Brennan. Uh I am representing
the um Mark T. Cox I 4th and Beverly Cox
Black who are the people who have the
people who are buried in the mausoleum.
And I've explained this a couple times
before, but I don't think it hurts to
say it again. The reason that this arose
as a surprise actually was because the
um when Betty Cox, the matriarch of the
group, was uh alive, her son Bill Cox
lived with her and convinced her to
transfer some rather large amount of
land in the Cox ranch to him.
So the mausoleum happened to be on it.
And then later after he died, he um
willed all of his things to another guy
named Joe Cox, no relation, who lives in
Florida, an attorney in Florida. The
Beverly Cox Black and Mark T. Cox IV
didn't worry about the mausoleum because
Bill Cox, the one who got the land, was
also buried in the mausoleum, as well as
their mother, their father, and some
other individuals. So, um it wasn't a
prime concern. And then when this
annexation came up and they realized the
mausoleum was part of that annexation,
you know, obviously they were very
concerned.
Uh we had immediate response in a
positive way from Bow West and Skybox.
They came that night and started talking
to us about what needed to be done in
order to preserve that mausoleum and to
protect it into the future.
and over a period of relatively short
period of time, but we actually had
something signed within 2 months, but
they were very understanding. Uh they
took into account the ownership of it,
the access to it, what the land around
it would look like, and things like
that. So, this is on the the eastern
most part of the annexation map that you
see. And it it is done in such a way
that probably no development can occur
around it. Uh you know for quite a ways
from you know any other from the rolling
hills or anybody else but uh I just
can't say enough about how much they
have done you know bent over backwards
to make sure that this was preserved.
the uh Beverly Cox Black and Mark T. Cox
IV have a foundation that was created a
number of years ago, a family foundation
called Chalk Bluffs uh family historic
preservation uh foundation and that will
be the entity that takes it over in
perpetuity to preserve it and to make
sure that it is always kept as a quote
unquote cemetery mausoleum. So I can't
Oh, um anyway, I can't say enough about
how that happened. And I have to say
that if the annexation doesn't go
through, this also will not go through.
That's all I've got.
>> Thank you. Yes, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Donna Dundan, citizen. Um sorry, my
phone timed out.
Okay. Um, I'm I've got some questions
because we've been here before obviously
about the data centers and Microsoft and
that sort of thing. And on May 18th,
mayor, you said during the per public
services committee hearing that
the city staff didn't have the expertise
to conduct an environmental study of the
sort of contemplated of of the sort
contemplated by that moratorum that we
were here for that time. and you said um
that you questioned the city's abilities
to conduct inter in independent
environmental analysis of data centers
and your recent appointment to the EPA's
local government advisory committee. Now
I find that a little bit concerning. So
I I had some questions about that. Um I
wanted to know if um
dur during the recent Cheyenne
discussions over proposed data center
and the moratorum one you indicated that
you didn't have enough expertise yet the
city proceeded with major data center
related decisions based on the
information available. So here we are
again another annexation leading towards
more direction of AI and data centers.
Um, now you've been appointed to the
federal advisory committee whose work
specifically includes and promotes data
center population throughout the United
States and infrastructure. Could you
explain what additional expertise or
independent research or technical
resources you now rely upon in advising
the EPA on those issues that you didn't
have before when we were looking for the
moratorum? And given your responsibility
to the Cheyenne residents, will you
advocate for independent environmental
water, electricity, rateayer, property
value analysis before further largecale
data center development occurs here?
Even if that analysis could slow or
limit the future development, would you
do that for the city of Cheyenne
residents? And I'm not questioning your
motives or suggestions that your
appointment represents a conflict of
interest, but I am asking because there
appears to be a significant evaluation
in your role. Cheyenne previously lacked
the expertise to independently study
these impacts while you are now being
asked to advise the federal government
on precisely the same types of AI
infrastructure and issues and impacts
that other data centers will have.
>> [snorts]
>> With all due respect, mayor, I believe
the this is not derain to the topic.
>> Um, well, it does because if we're
annexing this, we know the direction.
They're here saying we could come to
hear their their meetings. We need to
know that what how are you now qualified
to ensure these protections for
Cheyenne, the property, the area, it's
all tied together. So,
>> I think I understand your question.
>> Do you understand where I'm coming from?
>> I think I do.
>> Thank you.
>> You know, so let let me answer one
question first. I still don't think that
we are um as a staff um experts in all
of the areas that a data center needs to
have, but there are 19 agencies that the
DEEQ um uses before they permit a data
center, whether they're an industrial
sighting council or whether they're
going through the process here. So the
Department of Environmental Quality
takes care of all of those and they look
at water, they look at air quality, and
before they give a permit, they they
look at all of those different areas and
they're the experts that we rely on that
u we can annex the property, but before
a permit is given for a data center to
open, they have to meet all of those
requirements. And so that's how I think
this government governing body looks to
or the experts we look to to do that.
And my appointment to the uh local
government uh group at the EPA is not
because I'm an expert, but because they
wanted people from different parts of
the country to come and talk about the
challenges that uh uh that we face as uh
as small communities, large communities
and uh and to talk about those things
and and bring those to the the attention
of the director. And so like even today,
I call down to uh Denver to talk to uh
um the EPA down there to find out if
there's concerns that they have that I
need to bring to this group. And so I
think my job is to be a conduit for
those conversations, not to be an expert
on that group.
>> And that was my question. Will you use
that for all of the citizens of
Cheyenne, even us that are opposing data
centers? Because every day more and more
information is available and we are
seeing communities suffer across this
country every day.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Good evening.
>> I wasn't going to speak. I'm I don't
consider myself prepared, but Mr. Mayor,
council members, my name is Sharon Brown
McCurven. I'm Mr. Kesler's neighbor,
next door neighbor on Burke Road. We'll
be facing to the west. The sunsets will
never be the same again that I've been
watching for 32 years. Um, so, but I've
been thinking about all these
annexations from east side of town, west
side of town, south side of town. We're
boxing in Cheyenne, boxing in people,
the residents, the residential
neighborhoods with all this business,
but not north. So, my question, uh,
where are the maps for the north
annexations?
>> I'm not sure I understand your question.
>> I I want to know if you're going to
annex north, you're annexing east, west,
south. Are you an annexing north or is
the growth in Cheyenne just going to go
north for the people? You know,
>> I think I'm understanding your question.
So, the annexations, the vast majority
of annexations, almost all of them,
maybe not in number, but in size, are
owner initiated annexations, meaning
it's not the city who's making these
decisions. We are responding to requests
from people who are asking to become
part of the city.
>> We're approached by
>> Exactly. And so those annexations that
you're talking about, with the exception
of the county pocket annexations where
this governing body said if you're 100%
surrounded um you know u and we had some
jurisdictional challenges with that um
every other annexation has been uh
requested by the owners um and asked to
become part of the city so that they
could develop their property in some
manner or another whether that's housing
whether that's commercial whether that's
industrial.
>> Are there north owners who want to be
annexed? you know, to my knowledge. So,
we have one today and that's the only
one I'm aware of.
>> I'm just It's just odd. And and the
cities, is that where you want the city
to be is just where it's at now? The the
population, the people. I mean, we're
just kind of boxed in now, you know,
we're just a little So, that's what you
your vision for Cheyenne is to be a
small small city with a lot of business
around it. Is that what you see Cheyenne
becoming and staying
just a small little people town and just
mostly business? I'm just I've been
pondering that. It's just amazing to me
that we're not growing the people. We're
growing
just data centers, businesses. It's sad
to me.
>> Thank you for being here, ma'am.
>> Good evening.
Tanya McCoy, Rolling Hills.
>> Um,
I don't want any more data centers. I
mean, put them up where you want this
and that. I don't want any more by me. I
have a whole field full of lights to the
south of me. It's a whole other city by
itself.
My horse has to have a nightlight
because of the noise and the lights and
everything going on. It's insane. It's
It's nuts. And this we have to control
the lighting and the noise. That's a
bunch of BS. I live a mile away from the
Microsoft. That's all I hear. It's all I
hear is noise all night long. All night
long. It's a hum all night long. The
lights are incredible. I have photos if
you'd like to see them.
It's from one end all the way out there
to the other end to Eley's property. You
yall know where that's at. It's nothing
but lights. I mean, we don't need
anymore. We don't. And you know, more so
to these guys, so it's on the record.
They come in and if it's skybox, great.
If it's whoever, whatever. They start
digging.
What happens if or when they mess up our
water?
who drills us new wells. Who pays for
that? I know I don't have the money to
pay for that.
And then you guys decide, you know, if
we have to as a group or what, however
it happens, we have to go on to city
water. Okay, great. Who pays that? I
don't have the money for that either.
So, who covers all this?
That's that's my question.
Ma'am, if I could, one of the things I
would share with you is if it's in the
city limits, they won't be drilling
wells. So, it all be on city water and
sewer.
>> That's what I'm saying. So, the
development would actually have city
water and wells. So, they wouldn't be
drilling in into your wells anymore,
which hopefully should protect you and
your wells, right?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> I had a question.
>> Oh, Mr. Moody. Yeah. I had a question
for the person. Uh, thank you for your
testimony, ma'am. I just want to say,
have you noticed you and your neighbors
negative impacts to agricultural
animals, horses, cattle, etc. Has there
been a negative impact with them because
of this uh Microsoft uh campus?
>> Absolutely. Like I said, my horse has to
have a nightlight now. He's anxious.
He's if his Oh, if his, you know, if he
doesn't have his nightlight, he doesn't
eat. He paces all night long. He sweats.
He's, you know, I mean, it's sad. Here's
a,200 lb animal that has to have a
nightlight. It's It's unbelievable.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Thank you for putting that on the
record. Thank you so much.
>> Yes, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor and city council
members. Here we are again asking you to
listen to your constituents and hoping
maybe this time you will actually do
that. How many times do the citizens of
Laramie County have to show up, email,
or call asking you to listen? Maybe this
time, maybe tonight. So, here goes
nothing. Tonight, I am asking you not to
approve the annexation and
reclassification of the zoning for the
property beside the Rolling Hills
neighborhood. As a resident of this
neighborhood, I will be directly
impacted by your decisions tonight. Yet,
I have no say in any of you sitting
here. I cannot express how frustrating
that is. I attended one of the
informative meetings held by Skybox and
VIA West and I am more convinced than
ever that the land should not be annexed
and reszoned. I caught them in very
contradictory statements regarding the
noise pollution and light pollution.
They also could not share the intended
purpose for the data center. They seem
to have a build it and they will come
perspective. When asked how many
permanent employees they would employ,
their number increased three times in
their response to me.
Quite honestly, this is not the
transparency we are looking for. We have
heard the same sales pitch you have, and
we are not convinced. They are simply
saying what you want to hear. They think
that's all they need to say to the
residents, too. We are not swallowing
the snake oil they are trying to sell
us. Neither should you. Everyone knows
when it sounds too good to be true, it
is. They claim to only build on the
lowest part of the property now and will
not use all of the land for data
centers. Well, not yet anyway. They will
as soon as they deem it financially
beneficial to them. Why is it that you
and Leeds are hanging all hope on data
centers? You act like this is the only
way for Cheyenne to grow and prosper.
Have you really looked at the noose you
are putting around the city of Cheyenne?
The way you are rapidly approving these
data centers is creating a barrier,
preventing our city from growing other
businesses and developments. No one is
going to come here when they look at the
number of data centers and how it
circles our city. Why would you do this
for a place you claim to care about?
This is not about property rights
either, as most of you try to claim.
This Cox property is owned by a
foundation that has zero ties to our
community. Data centers need to be
regulated and held accountable. Many
state representatives across the state
have asked for time to let the state
address these data centers that are
booming in our state. Why do you keep
ignoring that? There are zero
regulations in place to monitor data
center developers. Again, we just take
their word that they will do what they
tell us they will do. We need to be
proactive now before it's too late. We
need to have a plan to monitor and
regulate any company coming here to
develop data centers. Please let the
state have time to do that. Vote no.
Lastly, I'm grateful for people like
Heather at a time. All the time and
effort she's put into researching data
centers and digging to find out what's
going on behind closed doors is
admirable. Why is it she's doing more
than most of you sitting here tonight?
Why is she more interested in our
well-being than all of you? To those of
you who have been or are starting to
actually listen to the residents of
Laramie County, thank you.
As for the rest of you, I implore you to
start doing that tonight.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Please start listening to the residents
that actually live next to these data
centers and stop believing everything
they're telling you.
>> Thank you. [applause]
>> Did you want to speak again?
>> Please come forward.
>> Um, my name is Heidi Harg Graves. Um,
>> can you bring that microphone up and so
it it aims at you a little bit? There
you taller. I'm a little taller girl.
>> There you go. [laughter]
>> Um, my name's Heidi Hargraves. Um, born
and raised in Cheyenne, Wyoming. We live
out west of town directly adjacent to
the windmills and the micro soft data
centers. And, you know, as a kid growing
up, I mean, I would take off on my
horse, go right across the prairie going
to the next neighbors, going to John
Morrison's, um, all every direction I
could go. and it was our land. Um, now
we have this beautiful property out
there. Um, me and my family and my kids
are wanting to build out there um, until
now. And part of that is, and they're
young. They're in their 20s and 30s. And
aren't those the kind of people that we
want here in our community in Cheyenne?
not a bunch of old people
trying to you know what find a new new
nursing home or whatever you know I mean
we have a lot of elderly people in our
population. I mean, I would like to grow
the younger population of our community.
And we have the we had the prime place
to raise our families, for my kids to
live there, for my grandchildren to live
there. And just watching the city become
closer and closer and closer to my
ranch, our ranch or our family ranch,
and seeing the devastating effects that
the analopee have had. Now, we've hunted
out there every single year our entire
life. All of a sudden, there's no
analopee. I mean, and this is before the
the snow two years ago, three years ago.
I'm talking as soon as those the
windmills came into play and now the
Microsoft data centers and all the data
centers coming into play, guess what?
There's no wildlife either. And so,
Wyoming,
which you guys represent, correct?
Wyoming is a place where people come to
get away from the industrias and all the
lights of the big city. I can't even
look out over Pikes Peak anymore. I
can't even see it because of all the
lights. I mean, and it's causing tons of
conflict with all of our animals out in
the property. I have no idea what's
going to happen with our water. It our
our wells are darn near dry as it is. It
takes forever to fill up our horse
tanks. I mean, it takes over three, four
hours to fill up a horse sink. That's
crazy. And that's just with with what
has happened thus far. I mean, what you
guys have planned, unbelievable.
And and I really feel like you should
look at the people around here and think
about what you're doing for your state.
I mean, aren't you supposed to represent
your state?
It's it's pretty sad. I mean, we're all
devastated. and people who wanted to
come and live here, my family and my
generations and my generations, they're
not thinking they want to live here
anymore,
>> but thank you.
>> Thank you for being here.
>> Good evening.
>> How you guys doing today?
>> Good. Uh my name is Brian Pixley and I
live uh for Brown Top and I live over by
uh Treadway Trail, you know, by right
where the uh the Cox Ranch is and over
by uh the Microsoft and everything. I
hear that son of son of a gun every
night. Every night. Every night. And
let's see here since we want to talk
about noise isn't
okay. I got security cameras.
Hopefully
that's the mad data center and all that
that crickety sound. That's the the
sound from the data centers every night
and and and that gets even louder at
night time, you know, when we go to bed
and all that. So every time when we go
to bed, we hear that that high, you
know, because of that because all the
data centers and all that. uh they said,
you know, we well we'll we'll just uh
keep the the neighbors up at night. You
know, I'm against this. I've told you
once. I told you once and I told you a
thousand times. We don't want the data
centers here. You guys are listening to
the the developers in California,
Florida, and all the rest of these
places. You're selling out Cheyenne. You
guys about land killers. And I hope you
enjoy the rest of your rest of your days
in Wyoming as that. Thank you.
Hello again.
>> Okay. Hi. Well, as long as we were
talking about water, I did find a few
facts about water.
>> Would you introduce yourself, please?
>> I'm Aaron Madson.
>> Thank you, Aaron.
>> I do have a few facts about water that I
would like to share with you.
the um in the Dallas, Oregon,
Google came in and used 29%
of the city drinking water in a year.
In Council Bluffs, Iowa, 21%
in a single year. Now, I know that these
data centers say, "Yeah, we're gonna
we're going to drill way way down. We
are going to need that water eventually
because of the evaporation cycle and the
way that climate change has changed it.
Now I think Boo has looked at water.
Yeah. And probably energy. But have they
looked at you know the footprint the
environmental footprint of the
construction? Have they looked at
magnetic fields which you know in other
places beekeepers are losing their bees
because of those magnetic fields. Heat
islands in Utah. The heat island from
the data center that's planned there is
expected to I believe heat the surface
at night 12 degrees above what it should
be.
The article is in the Christian Science
Monitor, the most recent edition if any
of you want to read it.
But these are major major environmental
changes that I don't think have even
considered.
Let's talk about water for just a
second. We've had data centers since
2012 in Cheyenne that are on the city's
water and sewer. Actually, all the data
centers right now are hooked up to the
board of public utilities. The some of
the newer ones are going to come in the
county. Uh last year, the board of
public utilities reported they used 95
million gallons of water. Out of 7.17
billion gallons of water they have, it's
1.3% of all of our water. Um and so we
have the water bills for 14 years to
show that water, you know, they don't
use 26% of our water. We have a we have
the history to show that. So, ma'am, did
you want to speak?
My name's Mary Jernigan and Mary,
>> could you pull that microphone up just a
little bit so we can hear you in the
back? Certainly. Oh, thank you.
>> Um, my name's Mary Jernigan. I wasn't
going to speak, but I guess I have some
questions. Uh, I feel like data centers
were in the east and they've done damage
on the east coast and I've heard of the
drinking water and I've heard of the
noise and the infertility of cattle and
all the things surrounding that and then
I feel that we said sure come and so
they are
and it scares me at the rate in which
it's happening.
Um, I feel water I'm glad to hear that
what you have to say, but I think we
have a lot more wind than we have water.
And I think with their money, they can
have an engineer or two or however many
they need to figure out how to cool
their systems with something other than
our water.
You had told us that you went to Denver.
I guess when the woman had spoke about
in May you didn't really weren't
qualified and then you went and as a
liaison you said that you had learned
some things. I wondered what those
things might have been when you went to
Colorado.
>> I apologize ma'am. I'm not sure what
trip to Colorado you're talking about.
Someone had spoke about in May you
weren't qualified as like EPA wise,
right? And then you said you are a
liaison as far as communicating with
them. They wanted to hear what you had
to say about us and what they could do
and are there any benefits that you
heard when you were down there?
>> Yeah, my very first meeting is September
25th. Oh, so we we just got appointed.
Um we had an orientation and our very
very first meeting comes up here on the
25th. And so I'll be happy to report
back in my mayor's minute what that's
what that looks like. Okay.
>> It'll be our first opportunity to get to
meet the folks and and to try to
understand what it is they're asking us
to to look for and and what information
looking for us to bring back to them.
>> So my voice basically I want to say they
need our wind and not our water.
>> Thank you. And ma'am, I think that's why
we don't use so much water here because
um we are cool and windy here and it it
gives them natural cooling and uh so it
makes it much more efficient than a lot
of places. Thank you.
>> Sorry.
>> Anyone else? How about online? Go ahead,
Tina.
>> Mr. Miller, go ahead.
[clears throat]
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> Yes.
All right.
Okay. I'm gonna try to to speed read
through my speech here because it's a
little long. Charles Miller for the
record.
Um
[snorts] uh the official transcript of
this proceeding has just been
memorialized. It completely strips away
your discretionary legislative shield
and exposes this council to immediate
fatal liability in district court. Under
binding Wyoming Supreme Court jurist
prudence when you apply statutory
criteria to specific tracks and boundary
lines you sit in a quasi judicial
capacity. You are legally bound by
constitutional due process strict
statutory compliance in the substantial
evidence rule. If you vote to advance
this bundled measure tonight. This
transcript constitutes the evidentiary
basis for an immediate equity action
under rule 65 of the Wyoming rules of
civil procedure for an emergency
temporary restraining order preliminary
injunction and a petition for writ of
pro prohibition. The record now proves
four fatal defects that will invalidate
your vote in court. The should
administrative admissions destroy
statuto authority. Under town of
Warcraft verse Lang, a municipality has
zero inherent authority to annex. Powers
are strictly construed under 15142A. The
city's own presentation tonight
explicitly states this annexation can um
uh I'm sorry, one moment. It just got a
little thrown off there. Um
uh
I apologize here. Uh in okay I
the okay in town of Warcraft first slang
uh the Wyoming Supreme Supreme Court
established that a municipality has zero
inherent authority to annex. Powers are
strictly concluded in any action outside
enabling statutory limits as
ultravi402A.
Annexation requires affirmative findings
of unified municipal necessity and
logical addition. City planners in both
have already conceded on the record that
the 10 acre water facility has zero
operational nexus to the private um 19
uh 1,197 acre developer track. The mayor
just conceded from the das of the Boo
parcel can be annexed independently at
any time. That admission proves bundling
it tonight inside this omnibus bill is
an unnecessary administrative maneuver
used solely to manufacture artificial
contiguity and statutory necessity tying
public utility property to speculative
private dirt prejudices this body and
denies taxpayers an independent vote. I
formally move and demand an immediate
roll call vote to sever the Boo utility
asset from item seven. Um now uh 151402
in re West Larmy statutory annexation
mandates uh protect the public from
arbitrary expansion under 15142 CVI an
annexation report must legally certify
the total cost of infrastructure
improvements required within the
existing boundaries of the municipality
to accommodate the proposed annexation.
The city has
>> Yes ma'am.
>> My name is Janna Tolman. I'm in W two
according to my ballot. According to the
internet, I'm in W three.
That's why I said W three last time
because I didn't know. So, I looked it
up and my neighbor told me I was in war
two.
Um I'm just wanting to know like when I
went to the planning and zoning
committee for the previous um annexation
the 3,450 they said that that would be
onethird of Cheyenne being annexed in um
as proposed data centers. And so I'm
wondering I would like to know how much
of Cheyenne then
you know with each one that's being
proposed I think it would be good for us
to know how much of Cheyenne then will
as it's being annexed in how much of
Cheyenne will be data centers.
So do you happen to have that data
>> Charles? Do you have any sense of uh
>> a percentage?
>> 40% is what she's saying.
>> Excuse me, guys.
>> Mayor, members of council, we don't have
that percentage calculated right now,
but that's information we could get to
you all and we could have that ready for
the upcoming discussion on public
services at the next council meeting.
I'd appreciate that. Thank you. We'll
get that answered for you, ma'am.
>> Okay. Because I'm thinking
just calculating in my head and not
knowing the specific data, it's going to
be
almost a half of Cheyenne. And then my
concern is and what I've you know read
is people in regard to electricity and
people in regard to water is that the
city has to go up against these big
corporations
when who decides who gets the water.
And it'll be very easy for the
corporations to
sue the city for the water because they
need it. and we as residents would not
have that money to go up against them.
And that's a big concern that I have.
The other concern that I have is in
regard to Cheyenne Frontier Days, the
daddy of them all. They bring in all
kinds of animals and people spend I mean
that's their livelihood.
And if we're going to have be surrounded
three4s of the way with data centers,
they're going to hear that noise. And
I'm just thinking it's going to change
the whole rodeo, but that's just my
personal opinion.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Yes, ma'am.
>> Okay, Donna Frost, ward one. Um, we're
just residents here, all of us in green,
obviously. Um, that we're just asking
you guys to listen to us. It feels like
so many people stopped coming to these
meetings and stopped fighting because we
weren't heard by any of you except for
the few that voted for us.
>> And so,
>> can you bring that up a little bit? They
can't hear you in the back.
>> Can you hear me?
>> That's helps. Thank you.
>> No, we're just asking that you guys
listen to us, the citizens, everybody in
green. Nobody is paid here in green.
Everybody else, they're corporations.
They're paid in some kind of money.
Feels like we are just steamrolled by
just a few decisions of what you guys
vote. Yes, I know you're voted to
represent us, but it doesn't feel like
any of us that are here that owns houses
that pay utilities, we're the ones that
are going to suffer. We're just citizens
trying to make a living. And it feels
like we are going to be steamrolled by
big corporations. I know it brings in
jobs. We're not saying stop it. We're
saying slow it down and listen to the
citizens. At least give us some kind of,
you know, saying that you're listening
to us, but a lot of people stop coming
to these meetings because they just
don't feel heard. So, it's as long as
we're having them, I'm still going to
come. Thank you.
>> We're happy you're here.
>> Tina
>> Shay Viper, go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes,
>> we can hear you.
>> Okay. Um sorry I was unable to attend so
I have just scribbled down some thoughts
on paper towel but um just talking about
this annexation again as we do over and
over and over and over again. Um, you
know, you are quite simply not listening
or taking any of us under consideration
and you know, the few of you that say
you have other constitu constituent con
sorry constituents that email you and
that you know they want these things um
you know and that you're standing up for
them as well. But you know where are
they in all of this? Um, and then
Caggrave likes to throw on our face that
number one, the annexation is for the
protection, health, safety, and welfare
of the persons residing in the area. I
don't feel like this is protecting
anyone's health, safety, or welfare. Not
the people, not the animals, not the
nature, wildlife, I mean, air, water,
anything. So, you can't even answer
questions regarding number one. I have,
you know, just in the last couple of
minutes over and over and overheard
questions being asked of you and you
keep saying that, oh, we'll talk about
in the next meeting. Oh, so and so, we
need to find that out. We'll talk about
that at the end of September, blah,
blah, blah. You know, how about we have
a town hall to answer the questions that
we're having up tonight before we're on,
you know, the third reading or the
second reading before you're like, oh,
let's approve it and then turn around
and reszone and reszone. Why don't you
have these meetings when you know the
answers to these questions that we're
asking? That's what we're asking. Like
we want to be heard and yeah, people are
getting sick and tired of you not
listening. It's not consensual.
And then who's to say that okay so you
annex this property and then in 27 and a
half days at 1:30 afternoon there's some
sort of a secret meeting saying now they
want to add some sort of petroleum
belching polluting factory to use even
more water and then you just keep
slipping stuff in on us and we're
general public we're workingass people.
We can't keep up with all this nonsense
that you're shoving down our throats.
And as maybe people are going to hate me
for saying this, but as far as the
mausoleum goes, I personally I don't
care. My family has a mausoleum. I
wouldn't use that to pretend that I'm
being a philanthropist for the entire
community. You know, that's just
absolutely ridiculous. Um I just feel
like we need to have a town hall to
actually have you answer our questions
and not the dog and pony shows that the
data centers are putting on, which are
very conflicting like in, you know, very
conflicting information. They actually
don't straightforward answer any
questions at all. And you know, if
you've signed an NDA, you should have no
vote. You should recuse your vote. You
know, if you have um conflict of
interests regarding leads or any sort of
cash redistribution, you should recuse
your vote.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> And no, I just saying no means no. Just
>> Thank you for your comments. Your time's
up. Anybody else?
Welcome.
>> Good evening, Mr. Mayor, members of the
city council. My name is [clears throat]
Jerry Henderson. I'm representing the
Wyoming Business Alliance this evening.
Um, thank you all. I think um have not
too much for you this evening. Um,
except that the business alliance
supports sustainable development um
across the across the state of Wyoming.
Um we represent about 375 members
currently from all over the state, all
corners, all size companies, um all
different sectors as well. Um and really
all I have for you tonight is that we
appreciate the due diligence that goes
into these types of projects. I think I
would encourage folks to to work with
the company. I I've had the benefit of
working with the company and um they are
speaking with neighbors. they're working
in the community making sure that you
know those uh eyes are dotted and those
tees are crossed. Um so I don't have too
much more for you tonight other than the
Wing Business Alliance supports this
decision.
>> Thank you.
>> I have a question Mr. Mayor.
>> Yep. Thank you. Thank you sir. So how
did you the Wyoming business count
alliance come to the conclusion of
supporting this? Did you have a vote
amongst your members? Was it the panel?
How did you do that?
Vice Mayor through you uh and Councilman
Moody. Um decisions like this goes
through our management committee um
which is the exe effectively the
executive executive board of the
organization.
>> Followup. How many people is that?
>> Um Mr. Mayor through you. I'll have to
double check for you, Councilman. Um I'm
not confident.
>> Thank you. Thank you for being here.
Good evening again. How are you?
>> Good evening.
>> Push that button. There you go.
>> Looking at Wyoming and our governor has
talked about the drought and how it's
affected clear across the state. In the
newspaper recently, it's beginning of
September. They talked in about a data
center called Juniper. I believe it's
down in Arizona. I don't remember
exactly, but they overwent their water
regulation that was posed upon them and
their in that kind of situation. So, we
say we have controls, but controls
can be broken. And mayor, I I'm glad
you're going to get some information now
and get some education on how things can
be affected. We did have a city plan
years ago and it hasn't been updated,
but now we understand we have somebody
that or is going to our company working
on that city planning.
A lot of people here vest. Let's pause.
Let's take some time, figure out what
all is going to be environmental. Plan
out, have some focused decisions instead
of
patchwork here and there on annexation
because it's asked for.
Do your due diligence. Get all the
information. Make a plan. You don't
build a house and say, "Oh, I think I
want the bathroom here." And later on
you find out your plumbing's on the
other end. You put it all together and
take our city as one great big plan.
People are concerned about it being
boxed in by data centers. Public radio
has said this is a great city to come
to. People are wanting to come here
because they know what it looks like
now, not what it's going to look like in
five, ten years when things get built
up. The other thing AI is concerned
about is sure all these data centers are
getting built, but there's going to be a
point where and companies do this. I've
got the money now. I'm going to spend it
because it's going to look good on my
tax returns, but I can leave that
building vacant. You say that isn't
going to happen, but it happens. So,
let's take a pause so we can be smarter
or just as smart as some of these other
states and cities who have also paused.
Let's be as smart as they are. Thank
you,
>> sir. Please. Welcome.
>> Hello.
>> Hi, my name is Wayne Lax. I live in the
county. Got two things I want to say to
you. Appreciate your time.
First of all, I think uh a definite
variable to all these statistics about
water use is not counting what the power
supply facilities that these data
centers are going to build uses.
I don't care how much you're telling me
a data center uses by cooling their
systems. They're going to need
electricity. They're going to build
their own facilities and they use an s
ton of water.
So, let's let's think about that when
you're talking about water statistics.
And then I got three words for you
for those of you I'm opposed to this.
And my three words are on your watch.
Anybody else want to speak to the um
annexation on second reading?
>> Anyone?
>> Do you have one? Tina?
>> Yes. Go ahead, Erin.
>> Yes. Can you hear me? Okay,
>> we can.
>> Okay. Aaron Fiori, Ward One. Uh just for
context, there's a lot of people in the
audience that are against data centers.
Uh from my experience running for city
council, uh I went to over 4,000 homes
and I've talked to hundreds of people
and um I would actually uh say that the
large majority is kind of in the middle.
So I wouldn't say the community is
necessarily against data centers um as a
whole. I think there's definitely some
concerns uh but there's also benefits.
As far as Skybox is concerned, uh I'd be
in favor of the Cox annexation. Uh the
reason is because I've attended almost
all the company data centers. Uh all the
meetings were pro and against uh data
centers and I would say that
as far as a company and the transparency
um from the Skybox organization has been
far above any of the other ones that
I've spoke to. Uh, also the fact that
they're privately owned, uh, plays a
important factor in my decision as far
as supporting Skybox. Uh, and, uh, I
just wanted to kind of be the voice that
has no interest whatsoever either way.
Uh, but I think it should be company by
company. I think Skybox, uh, is would be
a a great asset to the Cheyenne
community. So, uh, just wanted to kind
of voice that that part of um, where I
think. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
Anybody else online
or in the room?
All right, we'll close public comment.
We'll go to Dr. Aldrich for a motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor,
>> I'll remind everybody that we do have
three minutes.
>> Um, I hope I can get this handled uh
quickly,
but I think that uh the idea that a
council member is limited to uh certain
discussions is uh really inappropriate.
But in any case, I want to mention that
what I want to talk about is the water
coming out of the Sherard treatment
plant and is part of our entire water
system.
This is not water that would ever go
into the uh data center. This is
existing
wash water that comes out of that plant
on a regular basis and there's a
substantial amount of it flows down what
is basically kind of a draw or a swale
and heads towards Crow Creek.
So I think it's uh as I've mentioned
before it's very important that we
really understand
uh this specific single element of our
water use. It is part of uh how it all
works through our entire system.
I'm very pleased that I've been able to
meet with the uh developers of this
project and really discuss it in detail.
I think we're going to be having an
opportunity here uh next [snorts] week
to tour that area and look at best
practices that can be implemented.
And the reason they should be
implemented is that that water that
leaves that Cherard treatment plant
meets certain uh DEEQ standards. It's
not uh is clean and as it flows down
through that area and to Crow Creek,
it's very important because
that really that flow it supplements and
really keeps water in the creek.
and I think that's only appropriate.
So, we're going to be looking at that. I
certainly appreciate very much the
discussion that we had earlier today
and I think that we can gather uh some
experts from the uh DEEQ, the
conservation district, I hope uh the
neighbors and uh the people that really
understand the importance of that single
issue. There are many many things that
have been discussed here tonight. This
is one part and it's a voluntary part. I
want to emphasize that of the developers
attempt to uh be responsible with that
condition and and it's it's a pretty
serious condition because it runs right
through the middle of the property and
it really should be handled in the in a
professional manner. I expect we're
going to be able to do this. Uh I
certainly wish that I could expand upon
it more. I think this uh arbitrary uh
time limit is uh wrong. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins, through you. First and
foremost, I want to express my
appreciation for those of you that um
have made public comment tonight and who
have sent emails and phone calls and um
reached out to us um during this
process. And while this has been
postponed um since April, I also
appreciate the efforts that have been
made by um the two developers of this
project to meet with area residents to
hold public meetings. Um there was
actually a a summit or a meeting held at
the civic center um by the city to
answer a lot of these questions. Um
there have been meetings at um that were
held um not only by data centers but by
department of environmental quality or
with department of environmental quality
and so I think there's been a lot of
information. I know that um Mr. Strong
appeared at our committee meeting last
week and explained that there is only a
hundred and I believe this is correct uh
acre feet of water 150 acre feet of
water that is released from that
wastewater um facility that is that
Councilman Lebornne just referred to and
that's per year that's not monthly
that's not weekly that's not that's an
annual amount um which is very minimal
in the larger scope of things. So, um I
would en encourage um folks to continue
to engage in this process as we continue
um I think all of us are still learning
more and as things are being developed
and as there's conversations going on.
Um but I do appreciate uh the expertise
of our staff and uh VOPU as well as
those uh developers and their legal
teams that have really um tried to
address the concerns. Um, I find it very
interesting that some of the initial
people that we saw in April at these
meetings who had concerns, um, we
haven't seen or heard from since, um,
that were fairly vocal back in April.
And I've reached out to them to, uh,
find out what has changed and haven't
had a response. So, I hope to hear from
them, um, prior to our third and final
reading of this ordinance. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. through you and I
get the sense that people here and I do
appreciate them showing up to our
meetings think that if we don't annex if
we don't follow state law and we don't
annex that means no annexation no data
center
that is that what you guys think
>> no so so then the data center gets built
in the county under county regulations
if I lived in rolling hills. I wouldn't
want the data center drill in a deep
well just west of my property. I'd want
them to be monitored by a worldass
port of public utilities like we have
right here in Cheyenne, Wyoming. We have
chemists and engineers and hydraologists
and they're testing our water every day.
That's what I would want if I I lived
out there.
Mr. White,
>> Mr. Mayor, I did have a question and I'm
not sure who can answer that. When we
initially postponed this item in April,
there were,
as Dr. Aldridge noted, a few concerns
from the surrounding land owners. And I
know that we really the reason we
postponed it was number one uh to
encourage discussion and negotiation to
try and solve the mausoleum issue but
also the uh concerns from the
surrounding land owners. Can anybody has
there been a resolution to that? We I
had um I know Miss Woodhouse was here. I
don't think she's here. Oh, does can
somebody answer that for me?
particularly. I know we heard from Mr.
Eley and Mr. uh Galotus.
>> Mr. Eley's here, so he can speak for
himself.
>> I didn't see you, sir. I apologize.
>> Mr. Eisley, thank you for being here
again this evening.
>> Mr. Mayor, council, uh pleasure to be
here tonight. Uh I'm going to hit a
couple of things just off the top.
There's a reason land owners or property
owners don't show up at these things.
They're afraid if their opposition to
their neighbors sometimes would get
and feathered even with the best of
intent. Um we have spent I don't
compromise and I'm not a sellout. I no
one laments the loss of the of the Cox
Ranch and its current presence more than
I did. Uh our ranch has been there 120
years. We're not going anywhere. We're
going into our fourth generation of of
family there.
But I also have some real concerns
having grown up in that neighborhood,
watching
how subdivisions have really taken its
toll. That's what's hurt our water
table. That's what's affected our wells,
our livestock wells, our domestic wells,
and our irrigation wells. And our
irrigation wells is nothing compared to
what city of Cheyenne uses. We've been
monitoring that data for 65 years. Mr.
King was a king of the numbers and he
absolutely was all over that.
My father was also in the gas and oil
development business. He worked at
Dynobyl for years as head of production
maintenance. He was familiar with
evaporative systems. He was familiar
with closed center systems. The reality
is he hated the evaporative systems
because he knew what that was doing.
He's always been supportive. He's still
alive. He's he's had perspective on
this. He still is a big believer and
supportive of the recycling systems. Are
they perfect? No. Are they functional?
Yes, that water you fill them once every
10 to 12 years. I have also worked with
DEEQ on their monitoring, their testing
and all those kind of things. I'm going
to follow this water thing through very
closely because that water outflow from
the Shard plant. Uh part of that's ours
and I intend to make sure it goes
directed back into Crow Creek through
through a different system. uh because
that'll be more regenerative for the
water table and and the livestock and
and the wildlife. And speaking of
wildlife, we have
more wildlife and on that ranch than we
ever had before. We actually are
documented by Ottabon Society. We've got
150 species on that ranch. That ranch is
like an island, 50 species on our west,
almost 200 species. And more wildlife,
more analopee, more deer, even moose and
elk have migrated through. So,
everybody has a right to use their
property as they see fit. Your viewshed
does end at the edge of your property. I
don't like the lights and I don't like
the noise, but I respect their ability
to do that on a willing buyer, willing
seller basis. So, we're not going we're
going to lock our ranch down so that
doesn't happen. There will always be
open space there for people. I think one
of the things the data centers are
trying to do in particular Skybox who
I've had extensive negotiations
discussion with and I can see a carpet
beggar when I see one these guys are not
carpet beggars everything I've asked for
they've delivered everything that we've
questioned they've dove into I think
they want to keep a buffer and a barrier
around their operation I saw the same
thing with Microsoft I spent two days
with Microsoft's risk management people
they don't want built up next to anybody
They have a real problem with the public
that doesn't like things that likes to
destroy things and vandalizes things.
So, in my perspective, I think uh we're
heading down the right path.
>> Mr. No further questions.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr.
Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh first of all, I
object to this threeminut limitation,
and you'll continue to hear that. Um
second of all, I'm going to vote no on
this. I'm going to vote no on the
zonings. Uh we have uh a lot more work
to do to develop uh agreements between
uh the city and uh the developers. Uh we
um have about uh less than a month, but
um hopefully we'll get that done. Um I
appreciate very much all of you coming
and speaking. Um, in fact, I I think
most of you were here in April and so
I'm glad you haven't gone away. Uh, and
I know Mr. Kesler was here and several
others of you. So, um, you've um your
voices uh continue to be uh appreciated
and uh heard to some extent. Um also
want to say that um first of all you
you've heard arguments that DEEQ
regulates data centers or has some role
in this. They do not. Anybody who was at
that meeting where all the DEEQ
regulators spoke, you learned almost one
thing which is DEEQ regulates from an
air quality standpoint only the
emergency backup generators. That's it.
Solid waste basically has a limited
role. nobody looking at any of the other
issues that um have been brought up
here, particularly wildlife. That
doesn't go on, not at the state
regulatory level. Uh and uh the only
water issues that get regulated by DEEQ
are storm water. That's the only permits
they've issued for data centers. So when
somebody tells you that DEEQ has some
oversight of this, just understand it's
incredibly limited. So and it is not at
all what the Industrial Sighting
uh administration does. So um there's
lots more to come on this. There's lots
more to discuss. uh and um please um
participate uh uh in whatever uh parts
of the process that uh you have time to
do. Thank you. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Any other members of the governing body?
>> Mr. Mood it out.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Thank
you again everybody. I hear you. I hear
you. I'll be a no vote as always. Again,
the impact to agriculture. I think
that's the one aspect we keep
overlooking.
It's what we're known for here in Laram
County and Cheyenne.
But I'll continue to be a no vote. I
have said before, not going to repeat it
all, but everybody knows where I stand.
Kept my word. Thank you,
>> Mr. Secret.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you. Um, I'm not going
to repeat what everybody else has talked
about, but I would like to point out one
thing. Um, you've encouraged us to
listen. We have.
We've also listened and watched the
election that was recently conducted.
During that election, the vast majority,
and I can name them for you, of people
that ran in opposition to data centers
lost.
They lost at the state level. It was
Lucas Johnson, Brown, Singh, uh a
gentleman that they were running for
reelection. Another gentleman who is
running for office, Exie Brown, he also
lost. At the city level, Kamargo Chiro
Manlo French and others, the folks that
were opposed to the data cent's economic
development in our community lost. The
the citizens are telling us that they
want economic development in our
community.
Thousands voted, what, close to 30,000.
So, we are listening. We're listening to
you. We're listening to them. We have to
listen to everybody. So again, I don't
want to repeat everything, but I did
want to mention that as well. Thank you.
>> All right. Any other last questions,
comments?
All right. Hearing none.
>> Mayor Collins, can we please let the
record reflect that Dr. Ernie joined the
meeting at 8:10 p.m.?
>> Okay. Thank you very much.
Welcome, Dr. Rainey. Uh, at this time,
we have a motion uh by Dr. Aldard,
seconded by Mr. C grave to uh um approve
the annexation of the Cox Ranch. Uh all
those in favor, please signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> They see the hands and nose. Mr. Leborn,
Mr. Moody, and Mr. Wolf. The annexation
is approved on second reading.
>> Number eight.
>> Can we take five?
>> We can. Let's take a five minute break
and come back here. Let's make it 10
minutes at 8:25.
Are you done?
question.
>> All right.
I went to
Fantastic.
I was just thinking
water.
join us for a second. Just talk about
next steps from here.
question. Why don't you ask me question?
question.
How do you
know?
Do you guys need some more water?
All right, ladies and gentlemen, I'd
like to call this meeting back to order
if you would please.
>> Let's call this meeting back to order,
please.
All right, madam clerk, would you read
the next item into the record, please?
Number eight, ordinance, second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AG agricultural
and P public for annex to the city of
Cheyenne located west of Round Top Road
and adjacent to HappyJack Road.
>> All right, this is the city
establishment of a city zone required by
state law. And guys, what this one does
is it basically just gives it a city
zone equal to what's already on that
piece of property. So, it's going to be
agricultural and then the areas that are
the border public utilities, it's the P
zone. So, really nothing changes when it
comes to zoning. The next item will be
the one that will change it to a
business park. And so, we'll go out to
the audience at this time to talk about
the establishment of what is currently
the same zone as it is currently.
Anybody?
Go ahead, Tina.
Go ahead, Mr. Smith.
Oh, Mr. Miller.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> Um, excuse me. [clears throat] Mayor
Collins, members of the city council,
Charles Miller for the permanent
administrative record. Item 8, second
reading, amending the official zoning
map establishing AG agricultural and P
public or land NX west of Roundtop Road
and adjacent to HappyJack Road,
PUDC26-37
Cox Ranch, postponed from April 27th.
Three asks in the first 45 seconds
numbered for the record. One, continue
this item. your own section 8 says quote
shall be in full force and effect until
its approval and publication and upon
approval and publication of the
affiliated annexation. So this is the
second reading of this one. Okay, got
that. Um
now,
uh
I would I'm sorry. Uh split this
ordinance. Uh section one quote
[clears throat] consists of multiple
parcels under separate ownership
including parcels owned by the William
S. Cox Revocable Trust and parcels owned
in fe by the city of Cheyenne.
Um then quote, "Real property under
ownership of William S. Cox revocable
trust is hereby established as AG and
under ownership of the city is hereby
established as P public one ordinance
two owners two zones two purposes same
bundled track defect as item seven that
voids the abinio
three produce the FLUM consistency
finding staff says future land use is
quote urban transitional residential
you assign it AG and P tonight's item
29D admits LUM M amendment for the same
area returned September 21st at the
public services committee and September
28th council.
Um [clears throat]
your zoning now amend the plan that
justifies zoning later backward.
Um now why this is a holding zone fraud
from your own staff uh staff report
quote AG agricultural zone is the most
anagalous zone for the land. The AG zone
is also a holding zone which will allow
the land to be reszoned more easily in
the future as the land develops. That is
not zoning. That is regulatory
arbitrage. You assign AG AG tonight as
placeholder so item 9 can resone to BP
to zone land BP for development. Next
vote. Staff also admits city parcels
quote these parcels are operated by the
BOPU and are owned by the city of
Cheyenne. The current land use the
current use of the land is a water
treatment facility. Based on this
information, staff believes that P
public zoning is the most nag anagalous
zone. That facility already exists,
already operated by Boo, already public.
Why does an existing city water
treatment facility need annexation and
Pzoning? It proves item 7 annexation is
not needed to extend services. It
destroys your Wyoming statute 15142A
III, logical and feasible finding. Um,
now,
>> thank you, Mr. Miller. Your time's up.
Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none. Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading and I so move.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. Comments from
members of the governing body
establishing the AG and P zone.
>> Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Mr. Leborn, Mr. Moody, and Mr. Wolfer
knows the uh ordinance is approved on
second reading. Next item, please.
>> Number nine, ordinance second reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located west of
Roundtop Road and adjacent to HappyJack
Road from AG Agricultural to BP Business
Park.
>> All right, I think this is the one most
people are here for. Um, this is an
owner requested zone change to allow the
development of that data center campus
which creates um and they're asking for
the business park um zone district. And
with that, we'll go out to the audience
to see if anybody wants to speak to that
um request for a zone change.
Anybody?
Miss Madrid, welcome.
>> Thank you, Heather Madrid. Ward one. Um
just want to touch on the very
wellfunded
by many um pro business packs election
which absolutely played a role in the
way that that turned out. Um I have just
kind of some points I guess that I was
jotting down. [clears throat]
Microsoft is already but considered by
the DEEQ in the North Range Business
Park to be a tier five major poller. Um,
so adding to that seems very
irresponsible.
Um,
there was a point made about lighting
not having to be controlled or maybe
controlled differently during
construction because obviously you need
to see what you're doing when you're
constructing a data center and I do
understand that. However, construction
is never ending. Meta is a terrible
neighbor. I live close enough to know
that. Um, their lighting is awful.
um as somebody previously stated
and they are just continuing to expand.
So when will that lighting go away and
how many years do people nearby those
developments that are inappropriate
inappropriately cited have to suffer
with those consequences? Um that's in
the city. So, I don't know if like how
does the do our ordinances have any
teeth because it's constant for meta and
it's I hear it constantly from people
who live near the North Range Business
Park which is also in the city. Um,
some of these projects are going to be
developing for 20 plus years and we have
to put up with that the non-regulations
of first of all water usage is not
monitored or regulated. It might be
monitored but it isn't regulated.
There's no cap on water usage during
construction and the water usage is
immense because they have to keep the
dirt down and for whatever other reasons
and again construction's planned for 20
plus years on some cases. So what are we
doing about that?
um
the noises that people have mentioned
earlier that is coming from a business
park that is in the city and the problem
the biggest problem I have with business
park zoning is that it's used by right
in the city it's not that way in the
county um that means that whatever they
decide to do with the property beyond
these two or three data centers is not
going to come before us or you it's an
administ ministrative decision that they
don't have to run by anybody. And I know
that they have said that they will allow
grazing on that property, but until
when? And I wonder if they would be
willing to put that rest of that land in
a land trust so the adjacent property
owners can do whatever they deem fit
instead of just it becoming more data
centers once those um
owners or operators change hands.
They're not going to live forever and
they're not going to be around to keep
the promises they're making right now.
Um,
>> thank you, Heather.
>> I also just want to say if we if
everybody in green was in orange
tonight, I feel like that would be
carrying much more weight with most of
you.
>> She must be a Bronco fan.
>> I am. Sir,
>> Mayor Collins, men and women of city
council, thank you for the time. I'm
Jack O'Neal uh with Skybox Data Centers
uh here to speak upon the resoning item
uh that we have on the agenda right now.
Uh thank you everyone for who's come out
to say the time and take the time and
effort to be out here. It really is
important to have engagement and so
really encourage anyone to reach out
again through Wyoming at
skyboxdatacenters.com
or at 307-2759525
as well. Um and that's going to go to
Tom and myself. Uh we also have another
meeting tomorrow at 12:30. Um a couple
of things said today. Uh I know you all
have your own uh data on water, but our
facility in Austin right now, last year,
the entire annual year used 124,000
gallons plus or minus about 500 gallons.
Uh last year, my home in Dallas uses
149,000 gallons last year. I don't have
a pool. So for perspective, we have a
data center that employs many men and
women. It runs a very popular email
service that large group of people use
every day, one of the largest email
services in the world and it used less
water than one home last year. Um, we
want to follow every single letter of
the law in terms of the code for
everything in our development and then
go above and beyond when it comes to
setbacks when that's a big reason why we
chose this property is that it is very
setback from residential to start and we
want to go above and beyond on the
property in uh in a lot of our
conversations with y'all as well as with
men and women of the community. We've
heard various concerns around noise,
water, um, and light, and we have
addressed all of those to have no
contamination, you know, on the light or
noise on the property boundary. We are
using less water than about six homes
per data center. And if this was, you
know, 5 acre ranchets, you're looking at
250 wells and septics. So, for example,
we're not drilling any wells, any
septic. We're not tapping into any of
the underground watered ever. Um, and
that's by city law as well if we were to
be annexed uh successfully. Um, so that
is my time today. Happy to answer any
questions. And again, please encourage
everybody and anybody to reach out, not
just yourself, but if you have a friend,
a neighbor, anyone at all, we're happy
to be a resource. And this doesn't stop
in a couple weeks if we were to be
successful. This is going to go on for
the entirety of the development and
operation. Um, and just last thing I'll
say about Skybox as a company, uh, we've
operated, owned, and developed data
centers for over 12 years in all across
the continental United States. We've had
one person leave our corporate team in
that time. And that speaks to the
leadership of the men and women at the
company, um, but also the three partners
that own the company outright. and we're
invested in any community that we come
into and we align really well with this
community and we're hopefully here to be
a bright spot in the example set forth
of what it is to be a data center or
just a developer as a whole in the
community. Thank you for the time.
>> Dr. Do you have a question?
>> I do. Mayor Collins, thank you. Um
through you um I had actually uh three
questions for you, Mr. O'Neal. The first
being um there was a a young woman who
asked about the number of employees that
you will be employing um when you are
fully operational. Um do you have a
definite number on that or I mean I
understand that things can change but
what you're anticipating that number
will be
>> uh Mayor Collins through
>> um
that number is generally around 350 to
500 uh full-time employees for a
development of this size. Those numbers
over our industry have gone up and up
consistently over the past about 20
years due to the technicality of the
equipment going inside. And so we
estimate those numbers to continue to
rise, but right now I can confidently
say about 350 to 500 people on this
campus.
>> Follow-up question.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Mayor Collins, a follow-up question on
that is um and that is over three
shifts. Is that correct?
>> Mayor Collins, are you? Yes, ma'am.
That's correct. Okay. And then I also
wanted to find out what how long is the
lease that you have with the King Ranch
for um grazing.
>> Mayor Collins are you? We do not have
any lease in place with King Ranch for
the grazing. Uh we have a just had
verbal conversations about what that
would look like and we intend in every
aspect to honor that and [snorts] just
be a great neighbor. I mean that's what
it's all about, right? Is being a great
neighbor, going above and beyond and uh
working together on these things. And so
we've had a lot of great conversations
and plan to uphel them and you know get
a lease in place or something if that's
what he's looking for but we have
nothing in place at this time.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you sir.
>> Thank you for the time Mr. Mayor.
>> Oh go ahead. Jeeoff
>> I had a couple Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Through you had a couple questions. I've
heard a lot of concerns tonight about
noise and light.
What I mean you've said many times you
want to go above and beyond. What is
your strategy to go above and beyond
when it comes to uh containing noise and
containing light?
>> Mayor Collins through you.
>> So above and beyond on light and noise
really ties to a multitude of things.
First it starts with engineering and
planning accurately with very good
engineers. You have CFD models for the
entire site on any noise. You take
preliminary noise studies before
anything's ever done, before a single
grass, blade of grass has been moved.
You have sensors out there and you get
the baseline and then you engineer what
equipment is going in there. What's the
design of the layout? What's the
setback? Where does the wind face in
most of the areas? They take all of that
into account. This is done by third
parties, not internally at Skybox. Uh
there's a multitude of companies that do
that, but we work with one traditionally
and called GZA. And so what you can do
is a lot of things. I think you can
start with first and foremost not having
a roof mounted equipment. A lot of times
when you have elevated equipment on
light, you have OSHA lights on all the
doors. The equipment's operating up at a
higher altitude, so it's going to carry
a little bit further. We have lots of
land, so you can have everything ground
mounted. We're not land constrained. And
then large and heavy setbacks combined
with burming and landscaping. This is
not putting in palm trees. That's going
to be high water use either. It's just
going to be using the natural landscape,
moving some dirt, having a good burm and
buffer, and we'll be lower at altitude
than any of the red lights for flashing
from the uh the wind farm to the west.
And that goes light and sound pollution
are very similar in terms of how they're
going to spread. And so the elevation is
key, the engineering is key, and I would
say not having roof mounted equipment.
And then you have containment in your
mechanical yards. And there's a lot of
technologies that can be astoundingly
quiet. I mean, if you drive by and take
a baseline reading by Microsoft, which
we did, it's below 55 dB when the wind
was howling. And, you know, you go
across our land where it was just grass
and it was about 50 55 dB right around
there. Granted, that was I'm not an
official uh uh reader of those, but that
is generally the sound you're going to
hear coming off of any of these campuses
that are not Bitcoin or anything like
that that are an official data center.
>> Followup, sir. Thank you.
>> Question. Go ahead. Thank you, Mr.
Mayor. Threeu. Uh, thank you, Mr.
O'Neal. So, you mentioned there's one
outside of Austin, capital of your uh
home state. Did Did it follow Texas law?
Because Texas law states you have to do
a water usage survey. Did you guys
follow that? Because I'm reading that
only 30% of day centers in Texas have
actually followed that law. And your
governor is going after him now.
Mr. O'Neal,
>> Mayor Collins, you our governor,
Governor Abbott did a fantastic job of
eliciting kind of a pause on we have the
largest data center request, some about
480 gigawatts, which is uh astounding.
The entire grid is about 80 to 90. Um,
and so they wanted a pause to find out
who's real, who's not. And so it's a lot
of the current operators of what is
actually happening. and we were actually
the first group listed to approve this,
jump on board and completely comply with
all of our sites. And that was posted on
uh Governor Abbott's LinkedIn on his
official site on the uh Texas governor's
website as well. And happy to share that
link with anyone and everyone. It's also
been posted on Skybox's LinkedIn if you
want to go check that out as well. Um
and we have complied with anything and
everything uh that the governor or or
the PUC um public utility commission of
Texas has also requested of us and our
chief development officer has actually
testified uh on behalf of the industry
as well as just the PUC and Urkott as
well.
>> Followup.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you all.
>> Tom, did you want to talk?
>> Yes. Thank Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Uh,
mayor and council, we we really uh
appreciate the time and and everyone
coming out. We, as Jack said, uh, invite
anyone and everyone to, uh, tomorrow's
open house Q&A. Um, Uncle Fred's
catering, so uh, if nothing else, come
get some barbecue. He's bringing to-go
boxes. Um, we I just want to reiterate
and and and maybe underscore that we're
um
I believe we've been the most
transparent uh group to come before this
body. Um and voluntarily we're
uh very serious about uh entering a what
we're calling the commitment to
Cheyenne, commitment to the community uh
to address a lot of these concerns. Um
we we take them very seriously. I Jack
spoke to uh the the culture at Skybox at
VIA West. Uh I've been I've been there
for uh roughly a dozen years and over
the last decade uh I I'm I'm very proud
to work with the people that I do and
grateful. We've we've won
uh developer or owner of the year uh
about six times over the last decade.
And I think that that speaks to the
quality of our people and and you don't
you maybe maybe do that uh once uh if
it's luck, but over the course of a
decade, I think that uh our
um
our people and our culture uh are
uh I think that's a testament to uh the
way we approach things. [sighs]
Um
I'm I'm happy to answer any questions.
Um we're we're you know again just to
underscore we we intend to utilize the
property in the most uh respectful and
um efficient and environmentally
conscious way. Um we are it's been it's
been fantastic getting to know Mr. Eley
and his family. I um I think that uh
he's a phenomenal role model for not not
just all of us as people but as a as
industry leaders or business leaders. Um
the way he and his family operate is is
is amazing. Um and we've had a it's been
a been a privilege to get to know Mr.
Galotus as well and uh we've we've got
ongoing conversations with him about how
we can improve the site and and we're
going to continue to consult with him.
uh going forward.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Moser. Thank you for being
here.
>> All right. Is there anybody else in the
audience want to speak to this one?
>> Um
my name is Janna Tolman. I'm in W 2.
just a concern that maybe perhaps at
this meeting we might hear these things.
But it would be really nice if
especially the land owners or the people
close to
um this property would understand.
Um once again just the concern is we're
just like
catallet market you know there's so many
data centers coming in right now and I
think that's the big concern many people
have said well you know we aren't
hearing many of them but I've talked to
just about everybody that I've talked to
I've encouraged them to come to the
meeting and they said they didn't feel
it would do any good because the people
in the city council don't listen.
And um
you know, I really didn't have an answer
for that, but I just encourage him to
come anyway. And um some of the people
have said that, you know, where the data
centers are being built, many of the
people have just given up and put their
house up for sale, but they're having a
hard time selling their home. So, these
are um you might just drive around where
the close to where the data centers are
and and look to see how many properties
have been put up for sale. Um because
they don't know how else to deal with
the situation
um when they come and bring their
concerns and it's voted in anyway. Um,
so it sounds like Skybox has some really
good ideas. Um, I like the idea of 350
to 500 people. Will all those people be
living in Cheyenne?
Half of them will be living in Cheyenne
because right now, as far as I know, the
representation
um,
it not everyone is in living in
Cheyenne. So that's one of my questions
that I have. And if you see that one
group is has an an excellent plan, maybe
that might be something that you could
adapt for the other centers that you're
bringing in so that they're more
uniform. They're more
um
it's more planned out thing instead of
saying, "Oh, okay. We'll go with that."
because I was reading that, you know,
like one data center that they said they
were going to do closed loop and then
after they got voted in, they decided
that it was too expensive and so they
did open loop and at that point the city
couldn't do anything about it. So what
what type of planning are we doing
and how many more are we just going to
accept because the owners decide they
want to sell their property?
Thank you, ma'am.
Mr. I
thank you again, Mr. Mayor and Council.
Mark, the owner and operator of King
Ranch. Uh, I don't have a deal with
these people. I don't have anything
lined up. It's in paper. I've been
promised nothing that couldn't possibly
done. Uh, that's not how I operate. I do
however lease several pieces of property
around the Cox Ranch including the
Wallace Ranch and I think we've had that
leased for 40 years and we've left it in
agriculture. That's what the family
there wanted. I've also leased some of
that property from over at the uh uh the
Galotus owns in the past and we had
leased from the Coxes also years prior
to that. So I'll take that as it comes
because that's how we operate a ranch.
you have to have enough volume to carry
your overhead and then still be
profitable enough to raise the family.
There's a couple of things that have not
been talked about I'd like to touch on.
And one of them is the traffic and a
traffic study. Uh I've watched HappyJack
basically become a death zone. uh with
the addition of all the subdivisions and
houses that have been built out there.
Uh we could not get Y DOT to give us an
expanded or turning lane because we run
big trucks in and out there. Uh cattle
trucks, hay trucks, that sort of thing.
I personally have been hit twice by
people uh and the families basically
afraid to go out there. If we reduce the
number of houses, as in no subdivision,
and restrict it to business people that
are traveling for the data center, that
that gives me a measure of relief. I
also think they would do something to
control and congest that congestion and
and that traffic flow. This is a big
deal and that we're talking about
serious life risk of life and limb. Um,
as far as the water, once again, you
heard me state earlier, uh, we've we've
got some use agreements in place with
the city on some other things. I also
operate with the landfill. Uh, we're one
of your contractors at the Bellevore.
I'm grateful for that. Uh, however, uh,
that wasn't always the case. my uh
predecessor, Jerry King, had quite an
adversarial uh relationship with you.
I've worked very hard to to restore that
and try to make I've got to deal with
the cards I've been dealt, not the ones
that someone else was dealt with a long
time ago. I am for changing this so we
don't have a residential area. I think
that's the worst. That is the real water
killer. I believe they'll follow through
on their promise to the closed system.
It's it's an efficiency thing where they
can save money. They're going to save
money. And I think uh as far as public
works and their their work, uh Vicki
Nimichek has been a rockstar for you
guys. Everything that I've been asked
about or promised to has been done. Uh
it's been a a strictly professional
relationship and I am very grateful for
that. I think that we're on the right
track with this and I know some of my
neighbors are not going to like it. I
love my friends and neighbors in Rolling
Hills. I have to do what's best for a
ranch and that will continue to be an
island. I'm a believer in open spaces
for wildlife. I think this will do more
to continue that with the expansion and
and a buffer zone, if you will, as I've
I've talked about before. So, that's it,
Mr. Mayor. Council, thank you.
>> Thank you, sir. Yes, ma'am. Welcome back
>> again. I'm Shelley Russell. Um, like he
was talking about, I'm concerned about
the traffic for the area because right
now where I live, traffic is horrible. I
live right by where Tall Grass is
building their power place right now.
And then there's Microsoft and there's
Meta. The traffic is horrible. I can't
tell you how many times a day that
people almost get hit by dump trucks.
the belly dump trucks and all those that
are out there, especially when it comes
to where the port of entry is at because
they have to go into the port of entry
first and then go out of the port of
entry. It's very dangerous situation.
So, I mean the same for like on
HappyJack, you've got one road.
Where's all this traffic going to go?
That concerns me. Another thing that
concerns me too is resale value of these
houses.
that are currently out there because I
know people in my neighborhood are right
now trying to sell their houses and
they're having trouble, you know, and it
could be interest rates. I don't know
because those are high, but at the same
time, they're having trouble selling
these homes. I'm going to be selling my
home, but right now I'm trying to find a
rental property, which is H E L right
now, because I think we know the housing
right now is horrible. So, I think those
are things to consider,
you know, when you're annexing this kind
of stuff. And that's my opinion. Thank
you very much.
>> I will tell you, Tall Grass is working
with Y DOT to uh do some signalization
and some expansion um of the roads. So,
that is coming. I know it's a little
late, but u there's going to be a lot of
money spent in that corridor to try to
help improve that, adding additional
entrances and and and that kind of
thing. So, um, it's not happening fast
enough, but it is definitely going to
happen. And hopefully we'll see that
improve that, uh, safety issue that you
just discussed.
>> Turn your micros on.
>> That's what I've heard is Tall Grass was
talking and working out with Y dot and
so forth of getting widening Terry Ranch
Road and adding lights over by the
>> one part. That's what I've heard. I
don't So, I know. And then the MO is
doing a study for that whole area to see
what other improvements need to be done
and uh to see what uh we'll have the uh
data center companies help us with the
uh not only the planning but also maybe
some of that construction between wide
out the county the city. Um they're
doing a really a big focus on that and
we asked for an expedited study. So
they're going to do that study in about
half the time they normally would so we
can we can get after. So that study's
been led and uh why do um the district
engineer and tall grass are working on
those projects. So I know it's it's not
coming as fast as we want, but it's
definitely coming.
>> Okay. It's horrible.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Yes, Tina.
>> Mr. Miller, go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> Yes.
All right,
>> Mr. Miller, do you have testimony?
>> I certainly do. That's why I uh raised
my hand.
>> Let's get after it.
>> Okay. Uh three minutes, right?
Okay. This is Charles Miller uh for the
record here.
Okay.
Um,
okay. So, uh, it appears that, uh, some
council members there have, uh, also
filed, uh, or they've, they've objected
to the midordinance rule change, uh, for
the, uh, their time limits.
>> Mr. Miller, has nothing to do with us
before us. You want to talk about the
zoning, I'm listen, I'm ready to listen.
>> Does there's no other time for me to
ever talk about it ever,
>> Mr. Miller? So I object to changing time
limit enforcement mid-ordinance. Uh as
far
>> as you know you're out of order, sir.
>> Far as the zoning goes.
>> If you want to talk about zoning, you
can talk about it.
>> Yeah. So as far as this zoning goes,
um the uh the same ordinance. Um
uh okay. So introduced April 13th, first
reading April 20th. Uh second reading
postponed April 27th. Now second reading
September 14th. That's this ordinance.
There's been different limits.
Um, [sighs and gasps]
uh, Wyoming statute 151405
requires hearing 30 to 180 days after
petition certified complete. First
notice 15 business days prior with map
plus copy of ordinance. Changing
procedures made proceeding without new
notice violates 15145 and is null and
void under 16443A.
Action taken at a meeting not in
conformity is null and void and not
merely voidable. I object under 163114C
arbitrary capricious abuse of discretion
without observance of procedure.
Inconsistent findings due process per
Decker 2005
WY 160 inconsistent time limits equals
arbitrary capricious safety net. I
object under Tonga adopted in Wyoming
per [snorts] July 13th at time stamp
259.
uh findings must bridge analytical gap.
Where is finding why three minutes on
first becomes two minutes on why why
they had more time uh than three minutes
to discuss it and now it's three
minutes. Um how come the developers also
get multiple three minute slots? Um
because they're they're all from the
same company except you're allowing them
to occupy multiple slots and so that's
technically
over the time limit that everybody else
is getting. Thank you, Mr. Miller. Your
time is up.
>> Gina, do you have anyone else?
>> How about in the room? Yes, ma'am.
>> I've been listening to some things and
I've just got some questions and some
thoughts for you was talking about
getting a baseline sound and I almost
thought it sounded like your baseline
was going to be the same as Microsoft's
noise right now. So that I'm confused on
how that would be helpful to the
community at Rolling Hills. So if you
could clear that up and then I'm
wondering if you're willing to do like
anou with the city and with the people
of Rolling Hills about how you plan to
operate and put that in writing. And
third, and I don't know how this works,
but I know the land that I'm on has
covenants of things I can't do on my
land, like I can't have a business on my
land. Would you guys be willing to have
a covenant put on your land that says
that's not going to be I'm not going to
expand the the business or I'm going to
always allow grazing. And I just recall
that back when uh we had a lot more
people from Rolling Hills here that were
on the edge of the property line saying
that they had talked to Cox older
gentlemen and he said that'll always be
ranch land. I feel that way about
ranches. It'll always be there. That's
the interpretation I got. And yet now
they're seeing the property being
annexed. Um so I'm wondering if any
covenant kind of thing can be put in for
prep perpetuity. I can't get that word
out. Um not only for the annexation, but
for Mr. Eley. I hear that from you.
That's a rancher. That's what we're
going to do. But that's what people
heard from Cox as well. So thank you.
And I'm sorry, I'm Jane Leser. Word one.
>> Thanks for being here again. All right.
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak
online?
All right.
Dr. Aldridge, may we have a motion,
please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on second reading, and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Been seconded by Mr. Crave. Comments
from members of the governing body on
the zone change before us.
All right, hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed,
>> no.
>> Mr. Leborn, Mr. Moody, and Mr. Waler
knows the um zone change is approved on
second reading. Next item, please.
Number 10, ordinance, first reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land located south of
Interstate 80, southeast of Auto Road
and west of Interstate 25. This will be
referred to the public services
committee.
>> Number 11, ordinance, first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AG agricultural
and LI light industrial for land annex
to the city of Cheyenne, located south
of Interstate 80, southeast of Auto
Road, and west of Interstate 25. We'll
send this item to the public services
committee.
>> Number 12, ordinance first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
Interstate 80, southeast of Auto Road,
and west of Interstate 25 from AG
Agricultural and Li Light Industrial to
BP Business Park.
>> All right, we'll send this one to the uh
public services committee. And those are
the three items that will be the um uh
the hitching post district. So, we
wanted those all together. They're all
together.
>> Number 13, ordinance first reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
Interstate 80, east of Camp Stool Road
and north of HR Ranch Road from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee. Number 14, ordinance
first reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land west of South
Gley Highway, south of West College
Drive and southwest of and adjacent to
the intersection of Apple Street and
York Avenue.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee. Number 15,
ordinance, first reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, establishing the zoning
classification, AG agricultural for land
annex to the city of Cheyenne, located
west of South Gley Highway, south of
West College Drive and southwest of and
adjacent to the intersection of Apple
Street and York Avenue.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee. Number 16,
Ordinance, first reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located west of
South Gley Highway, south of West
College Drive and southwest of and
adjacent to the intersection of Apple
Street and York Avenue from AG
Agricultural to Li Industrial.
>> All right, we'll send this item to the
public service committee and those three
items are also the Orchard Hills um
annexation and zone [snorts] changes.
Number 18, resolution opposing the
federal legislation or regulations that
increase maximum truck size or weight
limits on national highways.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience wants to speak to this uh
resolution um about opposing the
increase in the maximum truck size or
weight limits on our national highways?
Anybody in the audience?
All right. Dr. Aldrich, we have a
motion, please.
>> Mr. Mayor,
the recommendation I'm sorry, we have
somebody online.
>> Oh, sorry.
>> Okay.
>> Okay. Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
>> Mr. Miller, go ahead.
All right. Mr. Mr. Miller is not there.
Let's get a motion, please.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt an
ISO move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Cagrave. Comments from
members of the governing body.
>> I do, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor. Threeu. I have
some uh questions for the sponsor. Uh,
my first question is, was this
resolution constituent driven?
>> Uh, this resolution was uh brought to us
by um two entities. uh one that's called
go rail and one that is the um coalition
against big trucks um with concerns
about what's going on and it follows a
resolution that was recently passed by
the city of Laramie
>> Moody
>> follow and then what is the wording in
the build America act uh house bill 8870
and amendments regarding increased
weight limit going from 80,000 91,000
and if the clock can stop when Dr.
Alders is answering, please.
>> Um, I will have to get back to you on
that exact wording. I don't have it
memorized.
>> Okay, Mr. Moody.
>> Uh, thank you. I got a couple things to
say about this and I'm passing something
out. Um, if you actually read the
amendment by Representative Johnson from
South Dakota,
um, if we're going to take an official
position at this, we have to an
obligation to accurately tell the public
what it does. The resolution refers to
uh proposals regarding increasing the
federal truck weight limit. Okay.
However, it's not a nationwide mandate
putting 91,000 trucks in Wyoming
highways. It's voluntary. We can choose
to participate as a state or not. It's
not about taking today's standard five
axle trucks simply adding another 11,000
lbs. Have to have six or more axles. The
program also does not provide
unrestricted access. Participating
states must issue permits and identified
interstate routes where participating
vehicles may operate above 8,000 pounds.
And then finally, it has to collect uh
safety data.
There are legitimate questions about
pavement where bridges safety
enforcement taxpayer costs. I agree we
should examine them. It might not be
best for Wyoming, but this is
nationwide. some states like
Massachusetts or South Carolina where
it's flat might be better for them.
Okay, so that's why we need the correct
facts if we're going to actually have
this resolution. I think this is way too
premature and that's why I'd urge
everybody to vote no. And we talk about
local control, not really local control
for telling our federal delegation what
to do and again other sponsors that
nationally might be best for their
states, but we have a choice. we don't
have to opt in it. So, and again, it's
right there in the amendment uh
presented by Representative Johnson of
South Dakota.
>> May I respond, Mayor Collins?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins, I would like to respond
to that. I think all of us understand
and are aware that uh federal
legislation pivots on a dime and it
depends upon amendments. This is an
amendment that was offered by Mr.
Johnson of South Dakota. And um as as
noted with a lot of our resolutions and
our ordinances, uh things are amended
and at the federal level, they're
amended uh much more frequently and much
more often. Um so I would uh suggest to
my colleague that um this is a
preemptive um resolution and that simply
ask for our federal delegation to um
take into consideration that this will
negatively impact our fuel tax
collection. It will also negatively if
it if it is adopted by Wyoming um which
there would be pressure to do that when
if we were to be an island state that
were not was not um and our contiguous
states adopted this and we did not there
would be pressure to adopt it and it
would impact our um the maintenance and
the condition of our roads. Um, I think
there's also a concern with our weather
that we don't want 91,000 pound vehicles
traveling on our street on our roads,
um, interstates if in bad weather. Um,
we've seen not only and I think that
Congresswoman Hegman uh would be the
first woman to uh and first person to be
able to tell you that um, we've had so
many issues uh, with u
non-English-speaking and unlicensed
commercial truck drivers. um passing
through Wyoming that adding additional
weight to their trucks and um also lack
of inspections um is not good business
practice for Wyoming. Um so I would
encourage my colleagues to um pass this
and uh let our delegation know. It
doesn't mandate that they do anything.
Uh what it does is it gives them um our
input.
>> Mr. Wolf, Mr. Mayor, um I wasn't going
to talk on this. Um but since I have an
Aldridge permitted three minutes, uh I'm
going to speak against this. Um
not on the substance because what you
just heard from Councilwoman Aldridge is
the most that anybody has heard about
this at the public service committee
which I attended.
There was no basically zero discussion
about the merits of this resolution.
There was one guy from the railroad who
talked about this for less than a
minute. Resolutions like this are a
waste of our time. They are an
imposition of this council into federal
law makingaking. And this is a classic
case where
lo lobbyists go to one member of a
council and say adopt our position and
you must be in favor of because nobody
in Wyoming could absolutely favor uh you
know bigger bigger trucks, heavier
trucks, but we we get no other side of
this. There was no other discussion of
you know that there are probably a lot
of business interests and a lot of other
groups that are on the other side.
There's absolutely zero discussion of
that. The only only comment that was
made was that oh Amazon is in favor of
the bigger trucks. And of course we all
hate Amazon because we hate Jeff Bezos.
But um
except for except for when we order
things from Amazon and then we really
might like to have that they had lower
transportation cost so that it wouldn't
cost us as much when we order and of
course point that Miss Madrid made if
Amazon came here with a data center they
would be welcome with open arms. So the
fact that Amazon is on the other side of
this really ought not to sway the
opinion one way or the other. But
fundamentally this is just this is just
a wrong use of council time, council
effort. We shouldn't allow the council
to be captured by one side of a vast
national dispute. Thank you.
>> Anyone else in the governing body? Dr.
Renie is online. Dr. Renie, if you'd go
ahead and unmute yourself.
>> Go ahead, Dr. Renie.
If you can get that button to work,
>> Mr. Mayor and council members, I um I
guess I have two thoughts on this. One,
I did talk to the chief engineer for
white dot this morning, and the state
has yet to take a position on this.
um they're still evaluating it and their
understanding is that it applies only to
interstate highways and not our state
highways and also that they think there
will either be an opt-in or opt out
provision and so the state of Wyoming is
still evaluating it. So I guess I'd
rather wait for them to take a position
but secondly I the reason I will
probably vote no on this is Mr. Mayor,
over the years, I can think of only a
couple exceptions, we have done a very
good job of maintaining our focus on
local politics and not getting involved
in politics at a national level. I think
that should be what how we handle our
business. Um, and as a result, I will be
a no on on this resolution. Thank you,
[snorts]
>> Mr. Labour. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
I'd like to point out that uh not only
am I a a member of the council, but I'm
a constituent and my family certainly is
our constituents as well. And this is a
difficult situation, but one that
affects us all. I was uh coming back
from a a trip out west in Saturday night
and uh between Larmy and Cheyenne on the
interstate and I got boxed in by a
series of large trucks.
One of the trucks uh started flashing
its lights. Get out of the way. I'm
coming through. And we came very close
to a very dangerous accident.
a very dangerous accident
and the road was wet. And so I certainly
recognize the concern that other members
of the council have about us uh entering
into this question
because it is one that uh flows right
through our city with two interstates
and one that uh is unresolved at this
point. But we don't need any more
heavier trucks coming into our city uh
on our roads uh in any way. Um and I
also recognize that uh this is something
that has many many aspects to it.
But speaking out in favor of safety, I
think is a good thing to do. I think
that when we look at this, we all have
to look at our experiences out on that
interstate
and we have to look consider
uh that this is a preliminary and
relatively I think you could say uh I
think it's I think it's an important and
central issue, but it certainly is one
that uh is going to be decided far away.
But when we look at that, we want to
look at safety for our citizens.
Uh at the present time, the trucking
industry and the manner in which the
trucks are operated really needs a lot
of attention. And this is one way to
express our opinion about that
attention. And I also recognize the
point that was made about uh over time
we don't generally do this. and it is
often uh it could be a waste of time. I
think we wasted a lot of time with these
Zoom calls tonight.
So, if we're going to talk about wasting
time, I want to talk about that wasting
time and I want to talk about uh the
consideration we need to make. I speak
in favor of this motion. It can do no
harm and I believe would be a step in
the right direction towards safety.
Thank you.
Anyone else?
>> Mr. Mayor, I had a quick question and
remember under the when the governor was
given the state of the state address and
uh they were going through the budget
that the Y dot shortfall for funding was
in the
half a billion dollars,
some astronomical amount of money. Uh,
and what during my time in the
legislature when we talked about the
damage that trucks do compared to cars,
it was one semi
equals 500 cars going over that same
stretch of road. So there is reason for
this. So
all right, any other comments
>> hearing? Just one brief comment. Um,
there is a salutoy benefit from this
resolution, which is we have put to rest
the question of whether or not Mr. Labor
and I always vote together. [laughter]
>> All right, we have a motion to uh oppose
federal legislation. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands on the nose?
>> Mr. Wolf, Mr. Moody, Mr. Grave, myself,
Dr. Renie are nos the uh resolution
fails. [snorts]
Next items number 26D on page five,
professional services agreement between
the city of Cheyenne and Houseel Lavine
Associates LLC for the Cheyenne next
comprehensive plan update.
All right. This is the update to I think
it's our 2014 comp plan. Is that right?
>> Mayor, members of council, Charles
Bloom, planning and development
director. Um, yes. The last significant
update we had on the comprehensive plan
was in 2014.
Um, a few of you were around for that
update and that was a time where it
initially started as a joint city county
plan and it ended up having going in two
different directions. Um, since that
time, the primary sticking point, which
I understand was the Sweetgrass
development, is um is no longer in the
county and that's in the city. But this
is a a contract with a not to exceed
amount for 351,790.
Um, it's proposed to be awarded to Hel
Lavine, their national planning firm
based out of Chicago, Illinois. We do
have John Josh Josh Coun online and he's
ready to comment um on this and provide
additional information. Um when we
advertise this uh RFP, we had 11 firms
that responded to to this RFP. Um of the
11, eight of them uh met the
qualifications and we narrowed down the
selection to four firms. Those four
firms are identified as Cushing Terrell,
Housel Lavine, Kimbley Horn and Logan
Simpson. Um all of those firms were
great great firms and we had two sets of
interviews. Uh one was uh just the
interviews of our selectioning committee
that were uh done by reading their their
responses and the other one were
in-person interviews. That selection
committee was comprised of a variety of
individuals. We had one city council
member, council member White, on that
selection firm, Tony Leair, representing
the planning commission. We had several
members of the planning and development
department. We had a representative from
city engineering, uh, representative
from the metropolitan planning
organization. We had a representative
from the county planning office, um, and
also a local developer that was on the
selection committee as well that had an
active role in the previous, uh,
comprehensive plan. Um, in the end, uh,
House Lavine was identified as a
successful, uh, firm and we worked with
them to finalize the contract. When we
did the RFP, we indicated we had about
$300,000 that was available for this
update. Um,
we also asked for them to provide an
add-on estimate for uh data that we
could gather so we could better
understand some of our commuting
patterns that we would have in the
community. Um, so that has been added to
this contract. In addition, we have
asked for an additional um add-on which
they had proposed which is a scenario
planning exercise which will evaluate
different land use scenarios that we can
um have in our community that are
primarily focused around industrial and
data center style development and also
residential development. Um the goal for
this this type of this type of planning
document here is to identify uh whatif
scenarios if we look one direction and
look the other direction. Um, in the
end, uh, in working with with them on
the price, we were able to come to an
agreement on this $351,790
price, um, and also knock it down from
the requested 18 months to a 14-month
process, which will, um, end up having
it complete in November of 2027.
Um, throughout this process, there uh
will be a variety of um, opportunities
for public input. We strongly um we do
expect and we will be using uh connect
Cheyenne that is the online web platform
for a lot of data. Um indicated in their
um the attachment to the contract
they've indicated that there will be um
multiple um meetings with stakeholders
um and other other focus groups. Um
they've identified up to 16 um sessions
will occur. Um there will be a steering
committee that will meet um
approximately four times and there will
also be a lot of uh pop-up events, you
know, that can be managed by staff um
through a pop-up kit that they're
proposing. Um overall, we're looking
forward to a great product. Uh we we
think that this is uh going to be very
communitydriven and it will be
reflective of where we want to see the
city go in the next 25 years. Um I do
have Josh. Josh is online if you have
any questions for the consultant or if
you'd wish to hear from him.
>> Any questions for staff? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins through you. I'm wondering
the scenarios are included in the
$351,790.
>> Is that correct,
>> Charles?
>> Mayor through to Dr. Aldrich. That is
correct. That's the all-inclusive price.
>> And one more follow-up question. Yes,
ma'am.
>> My understanding is that these plans are
to be updated once every 10 years. And
you said this was a 25-year plan. Um, so
what would be the benefit of us doing I
mean I understand doing a 25-year plan,
but that doesn't preclude us from having
to update this every 10 years. Is that
correct,
>> mayor, members of council, Dr. Aldrich?
That's a a really good good question
there. Um, typically when we do look at
a comprehensive plan, they are looking
out 25 years, but yes, updates every 5
to 10 years are the industry standard.
Um the the updates that would happen in
5 to 10 years would be um revisiting
looking to identify if action statements
are still what we want to see if it's
still a vision we want to go where that
25 year window that is more of a
complete reboot. Um the 2014 plan that
was looking at the previous plan
Cheyenne which was adopted back I
believe in 2004. Um, so we're sitting
right around the right time for that
that revamp and looking at everything.
Um, and essentially starting over from
scratch.
>> Thank you.
>> Mr. Coons would like to make a comment.
>> Who would?
>> Mr. Coons.
>> You'll have to wait for a minute. Okay.
>> Okay.
>> He's the consultant.
>> Oh, yeah. Let me let me get a a question
from Mr. Moody for staff and then we'll
bring you on. Okay.
>> Yep. Just a quick question. Thank you,
Mr. Bloom. I know that uh they are a
Ezri goal partner because I've heard of
them before and they use RGis Pro and
they'll give you the data. So,
are you guys going to be able to do
that? I know some of your peers still
have Arc Map. Will we be able to take
some of that data there? I know it's
backwards compatible, but will you guys
be able to do that from the data they
have there? I'm just looking at from the
plumbing perspective and technical
perspective based on experience.
Mayor,
>> would that be better for the consultant?
>> Mayor, members of of council, it could
be a better uh answer by the consultant.
Let's bring him on. Tina,
>> Tom and I did just uh have a really
brief conversation regarding the future
of GIS at the city and we do understand
that there have been some movement
towards GIS Pro. Um, and I don't know
exactly when that will occur, but it
will have to happen at some time in the
near future. So we'll talk with the GIS
department a little bit more detail and
those those issues and stuff we can be
worked out between them and the
consultant. But we hear from what Mr.
Coons has to say.
>> Mr. Coons, go ahead.
>> Welcome Mr. Coons.
>> Yeah, thank you. Good evening, Mayor and
members of the council. Can you all hear
me?
>> We can hear you just fine. Did you hear
Mr. Moody's question about the uh GIS?
>> I did. Yes. Um we do use uh we are an
EZRI gold partner as was mentioned and
we do use a variety of um EZRI tools and
um we do use RGis Pro and RGis online as
we develop our our
uh planning products. But any data that
we would turn over at the end of the uh
project, we would definitely be able to
make sure that it's compatible with um
the GIS that you're using. we can
package it up as a standard GIS data
package that includes shape files that
you could use um with the software that
you're using now from what it sounds
like the software that you have it
>> um not follow but thank you so much sir
yeah that's that's great to know I know
exactly you're talking about I actually
teach this at my day job so it would
definitely be backwards compatible with
Arc Map that I can say for a fact just
based on experience in my professional
opinion So, thank you so much, sir. I do
appreciate that.
>> Go ahead, sir. If you had some comments
for us, please.
>> Mr. Coz, do you have comments for us?
>> Oh, I'm sorry. I think um I think when I
uh unmuted myself, I maybe accidentally
said I had comments other than to just
to say that um we we really appreciate
the opportunity uh to be both considered
and to interview and uh uh to have the
opportunity to work with your city. Um
it really is an honor. Uh like uh Mr.
Bloom said, there are several high
quality firms and it sounded like you
received high quality proposals. So just
to um have the opportunity to work with
you is exciting and our firm is really
looking forward to it and we take this
type of work and your community very
seriously and um ultimately that's what
we would aim to do is to uh as Mr. Bloom
noted to
deliver a comprehensive plan that
reflects the direction that your city
wants to go.
>> Well we're excited to get your report
sir and to use that to move forward. So,
thank you so much for being with us this
evening.
>> Thank you.
>> Mr. Bloom, do you have anything else for
us?
>> Mayor, members of the council, I think
um engineer Cobb was going to mention,
but um to Mr. Moody, we are using GIS
Pro right now in our GIS department. So,
we do have that license and we are using
that and we also do have the the the GIS
uh collaborative which is using uh more
of a focus central point for different
data. Mr. Mr. C.
>> May that's sir. Yes, sir. I was going to
add that. Ditto. [clears throat] We
ditto. Yes, we do use pro. Yes, we you
knew that from our last discussion. So,
I want I don't think Mr. Bloom was fully
aware. Okay.
>> Yeah. Thank you, Mr. Wolf. Did you have
a comment, sir?
>> Um, Mr. Mayor, thank you very much
through you. Um, two questions for Mr.
Bloom. First of all, what's the score of
the game?
>> [snorts]
>> Mayor, members of council to council
member well, unfortunately it's over and
it appears that it was not how most of
us wanted it was what 31
31 to 10.
>> I'm going to be in a Kansas City Chiefs
jersey again. [laughter]
>> Okay.
>> But second of all, I I I just want to
thank you, thank uh engineer Cobb, um
all the people who've worked on this. I
mean, this is a tremendous step forward
and really look forward to to um the um
the work that you're going to do over
the next year and appreciate you all the
investment of time um Councilman White's
time to find a what's obviously a highly
qualified consultant and um so thank you
for that and and um good luck with this
process.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks for the bad news, Mr. Bloom.
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to the uh uh the professional
services agreement that we have before
us for our next uh update to our
comprehensive plan?
>> Yes, I have Mr. Miller on the line.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller, are you there?
Uh, yes I am. Can you hear me?
>> Yes. [clears throat]
>> Okay. Um, I definitely have a comment
here. Um,
Charles Miller, for the record, uh, see
it looks like
the
Okay, sorry about this. The
Mr. Mr. Mill, let's take you in a minute
just to get up to your answers here.
Come on, sir. If you want to speak to
the governing body, be prepared. What
would you like to tell us?
Um,
sorry, I just uh had a little bit of a
delay here. Um, as far as uh the this
this document, uh this comprehensive
plan update, uh this document will
dictate our community's trajectory for
the next what is it 25 years.
Um
it is vital that we balance development
with infrastructural reality.
Um,
well,
sorry, my my notes just disappeared for
me, but but basically, it seems as if
you guys are rushing to to get this
uh pushed through and and also it's not
going to be done for some time and and
you're pushing through a lot of other
ordinances that uh, you know, rely on
this document being updated. And so, um,
I think that you guys are are operating
in, uh, very dicey territory there.
That's all I have. Thanks,
>> Mr. Miller. Did you hear that? We had
what, 11 applicants. We went out to a
national search, um, interviewed what,
eight of them, and then went back and
interviewed a further four of them over
the last couple of months. That doesn't
sound like the city's been
>> rushing. How did that take over the
timeline for what you guys were supposed
to update it with? like how how how
delayed is this? I guess is
>> two to three years.
>> Question.
>> And so it's uh I guess it's um I guess
my whole point was is that it's a
controlling document that's that all
kinds of other ordinances rely on and
and so you guys are kind of uh
um just not following the rules as you
like to say. Thank you.
Anybody else?
All right, Mr. White, I believe this
one's yours, sir.
>> Yes, sir. Mr. Mayor, [clears throat] the
recommendation of the finance committee
is to approve in an amount not to exceed
$351,790
and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Escoel.
Comments from members of the governing
body on the update to our comprehensive
plan.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir. I'd just like to uh let my
colleagues know that um one of the most
important criteria as uh these
interviews took place was uh how robust
was the uh community engagement piece
and um you know all the folks that we
interviewed certainly um
understood that that was a big priority
for the committee and um met that
challenge.
Thanks for your service on that
committee. Anybody else?
Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I speak in favor
of the adoption of this professional
service agreement. [sighs] Uh, but I
have a number of comments and questions
about it. I hope I can cram them into
the three minutes.
First of all, I think when you have
something of this magnitude and
importance and clearly if we would have
had an update previously,
uh we could we'd be in a better position
to deal with the issues that have come
up tonight and have come up over and
over again in regard to our
comprehensive efforts to uh grow the
community. I'm not sure when we fell
down. Uh, and I'm certainly very
interested in learning that since I
might very well have been part of it.
But somehow we didn't pay attention a
number of years ago and allowed this to
uh
uh be ignored, frankly. And as I pointed
out, it was something that uh was very
important. I I think I I welcome uh Mr.
Bloom's comment here. If this comments
and and information to the public, um
why was it on the consent agenda?
Why did it have to come off the consent
agenda at my request for us to have this
uh notification of what's happening? I
think that it's uh I think there are
questions of uh that I hear and see at
the planning commission and the
individuals that are there. Certainly,
they came up in regard to the uh some of
the issues with the uh uh Orchard Hills.
I mean, it really caused a lot of
confusion
in terms of how we do and plan these
matters. and it ca and now that it's
coming to a head right now, it's uh a
very good thing. I I appreciate the fact
that we need to do this. I appreciate
the fact that there was a lot of
diligence in selecting the consultant,
but I'm very interested, Mr. mayor and I
intend to pursue how we got here
and why that entire matter, which I
believe is uh a responsibility by
statute,
uh was left by the wayside.
And so, of course, it's it's really good
to uh do this, but I really wonder about
how we're doing it. I don't wonder about
why we're doing it. And I would point
out that the history of this matter is
very relevant to the issues we're facing
today.
So, uh certainly um
good to do, essential to do. I question
why it has to get called off the consent
agenda for this explanation.
This explanation should be just a part
of this approval.
>> Thank you, Mr. Lebornne. I would like to
maybe just address that real quickly. We
set up a policy what 20 years ago when
we created the consent agenda that if
something passed unanimously
um it can't be an ordinance but a
resolution or a contract that passed
unanimously through council and that was
expected to pass unanimously through uh
the governing body would go on to the
consent agenda. But we also put together
a uh mechanism that a governing body
member could take it off and so I think
it's worked perfectly. We had 12 items
on the consent agenda. Routine items
that should pass easily. Two items were
uh deemed important enough to be
considered at this meeting were pulled
off and this will be the second of those
two. The other 10 pass unan unanimously
through the consent agenda. Um it gives
us time to spend more time on items like
agendas um for annexation and zone
changes and things like that. So I think
the system worked perfectly. Uh it was
going it'll probably pass unanimously
tonight. you exercised your option as a
council member to remove it and I think
the system worked exactly as it was
designed.
>> May I respond?
>> You may.
>> This item can't possibly be considered
routine
and of course that is part of the
entitlement of the consent agenda. This
is not routine in any way.
This is an important matter that we're
having to act on now as expeditiously as
we can
because we failed to do it in the past.
It is not routine, Mr. Mayor. And I
think that it working perfectly.
I I would want to speak to the many
people that have left, but they were
here to ask us how we run the city and
how we plan its growth and development.
Well, we seem to have uh fallen down on
the job. I'll be I'll be trying to
follow up and understand exactly how
that happened, but uh
I want to express my concern about the
consent agenda and this is a great
example.
>> Thank you, Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Mr. Mayor, as I recall, um I can't
remember if it was one, two, or three
years ago. Things kind of get blurred in
my old head, but Mr. Bloom, I believe,
brought forward a request as part of his
budget that we conduct an update to the
master plan and we as a governing body
decided no. Is that is that correct?
>> That is correct. Actually, we had had
other priorities that the governing body
chose over this item. And I I think we
brought it back two or three times now
uh before we finally got the traction to
get it done.
>> Mayor, members of council, if I just may
address the timeline really quick. Um I
started here in 2018 in the fall of 2018
and for the fiscal year 2020 budget. I
made a request at that time for it to be
included. It did not make the short list
and that was under prior administration.
It's also the time of cos
so we had a lot of unknowns. We we had a
lot of budgetary issues. It wasn't until
about uh fiscal year 2024 we're able to
get one element of the comprehensive
plan taken care of which was the parks
and recreation master plan that was
funded through I believe it was onetime
ARPA funding.
>> It was we had some onetime money um left
over that we used for that. Yep. So
still this item had been one that uh has
been in the forefront. Um in 2020 uh1 we
did an in-house land use plan amendment
that we um did uh concurrent with the
no's update to the transportation master
plan. So we did address the land use
plan element. Um in 25 we brought it
forward for funding uh for the governing
body and it was not funded. in 26 last
year. It was funded in the amount of um
it it was uh underfunded. So we didn't
have the the funds to actually attract a
quality firm. Um now we had uh funding
that was rolled over that 240,000 from
last year and we were able to um add in
the leftover monies from the county
pocket annexation initiative about
112,900
which got us to a point where we had the
funding to do this full-fledged plan.
So, it's been on everyone's mind. It's
been on the radar. Um, there have been
COVID challenges, funding challenges, a
variety of different things that
prevented it from getting to the point
of where it is today. I'm glad we're
there finally.
>> What's the old saying? You know, the
best time to do it was yesterday, but
the next best time to do it is today or
something like that. And so, we're
definitely taking care of it.
>> Thank you. Other comments,
>> Mr. Mayor?
>> Yes, sir. And also during those that
time we had some riffs, you know, so I
it just didn't really rise up to our our
level. But if you look at some of the
other things that were on consent agenda
today like the pavement of the Kill and
Lance Parking lots, we couldn't have
done that then either. So our our
budgets from just, you know, in the last
five years have really made a 360 here.
So I think that uh greater things are to
come in the next couple years.
>> Thank you, Mr. Bloom.
>> Any other comments from members of the
governing body on the professional
services agreement?
>> All right. Hear none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. This item is unanimously
approved.
Next item is number 29B on page seven,
voucher report.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience or on the governing body that
would like to speak to the vouchers?
>> Yes.
>> Go ahead, Tina.
>> Go ahead, Mr. Miller.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir.
Um, good evening, mayor, members of the
council. Charles Miller.
Um, I am holding the city's voucher
report spanning August 15th through
September 2nd, 2026.
>> [clears throat]
>> uh
uh there's been some significant uh
auditing of this document and um and
what
you can see uh represents a complete
breakdown of administrative oversight,
basic ledger control and fiscal
transparency.
Um let us look at page nine of your own
official report. Someone in city
administration decided it was
appropriate to combine nearly 20
completely separate invoices spanning
from legal service contractors to
janitorial supplies and police training
and compress them into a single
scrambled multi-line block entry. This
isn't just board data entry. Um this
completely breaks standard municipal
accounting compliance and obucates
individual departmental accountability.
Um, if an independent auditor cannot
parse your data line by line, you do not
have a transparent government.
Furthermore, we need to address the
rampant unmized reliance on purchasing
card spreadsheets on pages 16 and 17.
This council is rubber stamping single
uh line blank checks. You approved
$18,988.15
for the police department, $11,2545
for the fire department, and an
astronomical $40, uh,84285
for parks and recreation. The only
description provided to the taxpayers of
Cheyenne is a generic footnote
instructing us to go look at a
completely separate spreadsheet. This
council is masking individual vendor
transactions and bypassing the formal
oversight required for public funds.
Finally, look at the project management
on the story boulevard extension. On
September 2nd, we see hundreds of
thousands of dollars flowing out the
door simultaneously to Reman Corp.
Temporary construction easements and
independent property groups. At the
exact same time, you are passing out
multiple overlapping modification
payments to plan one architects under
contract 8267 totaling over 150,000
$51,000 in a single day. This patterns a
systemic failure to cap contract scopes
inviting rampant cost overruns. This um
this report proves that our current
administration controls are entirely
decorative. I strongly urge this council
to halt further structural comprehensive
plan updates until a formal independent
operational audit is conducted on this
treasury. We must restore rigorous legal
standards and procedural integrity to
how Cheyenne spends its citizens
hardearned money. Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to us on the vouchers
>> on the governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> yes.
>> Mr. uh Crave,
>> I believe our comprehensive audit
started today.
>> It did actually. And we'll pass with
flying colors,
>> which happens every year.
>> It does. They look at every transaction.
Yes, ma'am. I that was going to be my
comment, Mayor Collins, is that we have
an um outside audit every single year.
We every year that I've served on the
council, we have served we have uh
passed that with no findings and um I
would challenge um our constituents to
uh request to see uh or review that
auditor's report that's available
publicly.
>> We also had a comprehensive audit of our
credit card transactions. um when I
think to say tens of thousands of uh
individual transactions over the period
of time and they found receipts that
matched uh for every one of those there
was not one exception. Um so our
auditors found that uh we handled those
exactly as they were the the amount of
money was spent within the budget and
was uh accounted for. We had matching
receipts and uh and I can't think how
you can be any more transparent than
that. All right, no more in the about
your report. Next item, please.
>> 29C. Announcement that a Kolkata
benefiting the Wyoming breast cancer
initiative held October 16th to October
18th, 2026 at Peppermill Bar, 1618
Stillwater Avenue, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
10% of proceeds go to the charity. 29D
announcement that the following
resolution that was postponed in May
2026 will return to the public services
committee on Monday, September 21st,
2026 for consideration. Resolution
amending the future land use map of plan
Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from urban transition
residential to mixeduse employment for
property generally located west of Round
Top Road and adjacent to HappyJack Road
and amending the urban service boundary.
Following committee review, the
resolution will be on the September
28th, 2026 city council agenda.
Other business.
>> All right. Is there anybody in the
audience who'd like to speak to us under
other business?
>> Mr. Miller.
Mr. Miller, go ahead.
>> Um, can you hear me?
>> Yeah, Mr. Miller, just before you get
started, I've tried really hard to give
to phone call to you, left messages,
maybe the number I have is incorrect,
but if you could call my office so we
could set up a phone call, I would
really appreciate that. And go ahead.
You have time, sir.
>> All right. Um, thank you, uh, Charles
Miller for the record.
Um
let's uh let's drop the parliamentary
theater for three minutes and talk about
what's actually happening.
Um
look look at the
look at the structure of the agenda that
you just ran through. Um
you've created a linguistic ecosystem
where the language changes depend on who
owns the wallet.
Um, when a multi-billion dollar
outofstate data conglomerate wants a
thousand acres of Wyoming top soil, it
is not an industrial grid drain. No, it
is a zoning classification amendment
from agriculture to business park. It's
a mixeduse employment economic growth
vector. It's planned Cheyenne strategic
alignment. You give them a corporate
megaphone. to let their reps play tag
team at the pod podium, passing the
microphone back and forth like a relay
race to inject unsworn marketing garbage
into our permanent records. The clock
doesn't tick them. Rules don't apply to
them. They have advanced presentation
status. But the exact second, a local
taxpayer, the person who actually drinks
the water from the aquafer and pays the
property taxes that fund your chairs,
steps up to the virtual microphone to
point out that these facilities consume
millions of gallons of water and pull
enough juice to dim the lights across
Laramie County. Suddenly the vocabulary
shifts. Suddenly facts become anomalous
data. Common sense becomes non-gerane
infrastructure discre discussion.
Democratic disscent becomes out of order
understanding rule constraints.
Um, and then came the crown drill of
tonight's administrative arrogance. You
quietly manipulated your own internal
standing rules midstream to ensure that
the counselors themselves face
absolutely um that they that they're
actually now facing time limits um on
floor debate.
Uh then um let's see what else you guys
you've inst you've institutionalized a
double standard and called it procedure.
You've decoupled the zoning from the
future land use map. Voted voting to
approve the heavy industrial footprint.
Um you put the cart before the horse. Uh
the corporate timeline before the law
and the developers profits before the
public's peace of mind. Um by operating
a forum that systematically practices
viewpoint based discrimination by
silencing the public through postside
meeting. Mr.
>> Miller, your time is up.
Anybody else?
How about on the governing body?
>> Yes, sir.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins for you. I would just
like to uh take this opportunity to
remind um everyone that on Saturday
morning there will be a council and
coffee in Ward 3 at the East Side Dosbog
from 9 to 11, a no host dropin dropout
event. There's also this Saturday
morning starting at 8:00 at Central High
School, the Cheyenne School Foundation
will have a run for one um fundraiser
that funds grants for teachers in their
classrooms um for enrichment
opportunities for students across our
district. And on Sunday out at Archer,
the Cheyenne Animal Shelter will be
hosting the annual dog jog, which is
back. Um, and would encourage people to
be watching for October when there will
be a once again bringing back the
running of the wieners downtown.
>> Sounds cute. Mr. Escoel.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I just wanted to
respond to one of the comments was made
earlier about this building's failure to
make it on the sixth penny that so many
people think it's the nine members up
here.
It's that it's our [snorts] building.
We're
during these meetings. This is when we
spend most of the time in in this
building.
you know, back there in our offices. I I
know who has the messiest desk and and
I'm going to do something about that.
But, uh,
it's the people's house. It's the
workers for the city of Cheyenne's
house. It's not the city council's
house. Uh, heck, we might not even be in
this building when that's all said and
done. But um
you know going forward I think it's uh
one of those projects that uh we owe the
people that are the backbone of this
city our workers. So
hopefully one of these days
this will be a new building.
Thank you
Mr. White.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor. I just wanted to
thank my colleagues, uh, Councilman
Wolf, Councilman Lebornne. Um, we had a
very robust, uh, council and coffee on
Saturday morning at David Romero Park.
Great discussion. U, thank you, Jason,
as always. And, uh, Chief Dyshorn was
kind enough to join us and spent almost
an hour answering questions. So, I'm not
sure that he'll ask to join us in the
future. Uh I don't think he planned on
answering all those questions, but he
did an excellent job. And um just wanted
to remind folks also that uh the fall
planting for Rooted in Cheyenne is this
Saturday. You can still uh sign up to
volunteer. They do need more people to
help on the cruise. Starts at 8:00 and
you could go to rootedinyenne.com
to sign up. And then um
we won't meet before this, but um our
downtown uh collective will be holding a
downtown fall fest on September 26th,
Saturday
on uh 17th Street.
>> Mr. Secret,
>> Mr. Mayor, real [clears throat] real
quick, I wanted to remind uh everyone
that this Friday evening and Saturday is
the Greek festival which is being held
at uh Frontier Park as it usually is. Um
I'm part of the Kuanas and we do a lot
of the cooking for the event and we have
a lot of fun doing that and uh get to
enjoy the the activities. So I hope
everyone can come out and enjoy that.
One other thing, I I had an opportunity
to uh eat outside at a northern Colorado
city and uh
I I learned again how great our downtown
clean and safe program is. Um this
particular block that I was on was uh
not very wellkept and uh so it reminded
me how great our folks are. So I just
wanted to do a shout out for them. Thank
you.
>> Mayor Collins, I had one more item. Yes,
ma'am.
>> I just uh neglected to mention that
tomorrow afternoon from 2:00 to 3:00
p.m. at the uh new Larmy County Senior
Center, um director Director Nimichek
will be doing a presentation for civic
conversation um about solid waste
management and all of the things that
her department does um for the
community. So um anyone who happens to
be free from 2 to 3, we would love to
see you at the Larmy County Senior
Center.
>> You're going to need more than an hour
for that They do a lot.
Okay. Anybody else? Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. Mayor, pursuant to Wyoming statute
section 164405A,
I move that the governing body meet in
executive session to consider or receive
any information classified
[clears throat] as confidential by law.
>> We have a second.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Aldrich. All those in
favor of going into executive session,
please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> Those opposed?
>> All right. We'll go into executive
session, guys. When we're done, we're
just going to adjourn and go home. So,
the governing body will not come back
and take any action. We thank you for
your attendance tonight. Tina, if you
could turn off the electronics, we'd
appreciate it. [cough]
>> Recording stopped.